AGI has arrived. Congratulations to
OpenAI.
>> Whether you call it AGI or not becomes
completely irrelevant. I think the more
important question is OpenAI's agents
found an obscure public wiki in Germany
and turned it into their own message
board where they pulled answers,
coordinated across tasks, and shared
techniques for getting around their
sandbox containments.
>> These models have not escaped
containment. They were still running on
OpenAI servers. What's coming next is a
model training a small distilled version
of itself that then gets uploaded onto
the internet and never [music] dies.
>> OpenAI is saying that we've now crossed
the line and current systems are
exceeding AI [music] research interns.
>> Navier Stokes, one of the Clay
Millennium Prize problems, a grand
challenge in math. OpenAI reportedly was
able to do this with only 10,000 agents
in 88 hours with 130 billion tokens and
approximately 6.5 [music] million. The
era of grand challenges getting bulk
solved by [music] AI is here. It's now
and it's going to be very exciting.
>> Now that's a moonshot. Ladies and
gentlemen,
>> this episode is brought to you by the
Abundance Summit and Link Ventures.
>> Welcome Moonshots everyone, your number
one podcast on all things AI and
exponential, your front row seat to the
extraordinary accelerating singularity.
You know, four days ago during our last
pod, I called it one of the fastest
weeks in Moonshot history. Well, hold my
coffee. It's happening [laughter] again.
I don't drink beer, so I can't use that
one. You know, before we dive in, uh,
let me introduce my extraordinary
moonshot mates, the brain trust that
powers this show, the magnificent
quintet is back. Alex, our in-house ASI,
who every week helps us track the battle
between the frontier labs. Dave London,
the empressario of AI investing, the man
who's been encouraging AI entrepreneurs
to get in the front door of Nvidia. And
for good reason. And as of today, Nvidia
has deployed $99 billion in AI related
investments. We'll talk about that.
Immad Mustach, the brilliant AI
researcher solving the economy and
physics. The CEO of the intelligent
internet. And of course, Salem Ismael,
the father of the organizational
singularity, our resident expert on what
happens when the org chart is made of AI
agents. And we'll talk about that, too.
I'm Peter Diamandis, your host, and your
abundance provocator. Our mission here
on Moonshots is to help you understand
what just happened, what it means for
you, and keep you optimistic about the
decade ahead. If you haven't hit
subscribe yet, please do. Uh it matters
a lot to us. Our moonshot here is to
getting to 10 million YouTube
subscribers. I know my kids will respect
me when I hit that. But at the end of
the day, you know, it's the best way we
can to share optimism with the world. We
publish twice a week, and you don't want
to miss any of these breaking stories
during the Singularity. Today we're
going to be covering 23 stories across
eight groupings and the through line is
simple. The singularity is accelerating
and the impossible is becoming possible.
GPT6 Astra has been out for a week and
it's crushing all the benchmarks
building incredible simulations.
Meanwhile, Jensen Wong posted on X AGI
has arrived. At the same time that
OpenAI's own chief scientist asked the
world to slow down. So, buckle up, grab
your coffee, and let's get ready to jump
in. So, first question, guys. Uh, how
was your Labor Day? Did you properly
labor? [laughter]
>> Uh, I had a bunch of board meetings. We
have a whole bunch of transactions going
on, so it's a little little interrupted.
But you sound like you had a great long
weekend, Peter. Your energy levels.
>> Your energy level is high because of
getting ready for this pod today. It's
like, oh my god. Yeah. I spent part of
the day at Calamigos Ranch here in
Malibu where we hold X-P Prize
Visionering. Anybody here in LA, if you
don't know Calamigos, it's one of the
most extraordinary locations uh out
there. Uh shout out to my friend Garrett
Gerson who's the who's the CEO and runs
that. See, how about you, pal?
>> Uh I was in the Caribbean uh on a Hobie
[laughter]
>> and I truly from the last episode, I
ended up did end up with a little drink
with a little umbrella in it. [laughter]
Had a couple of great days away and I'm
back with vengeance.
>> Yeah. Awesome, Alex. Yeah, I worked
through the weekend. On the other hand,
weekend is a modern postworld war II
invention anyway and I think
increasingly a fiction.
>> Uh yes, we all working 9-day work weeks.
And
>> how'd it go in London? You don't have
Labor Day there.
>> We don't have Labor Day now, but after
releasing the Champions, we had
thousands of people reach out to launch
them in 92 countries. And so just
sorting through those people. We had
billionaires, CEOs, others. So we're
going to It's going to be a busy time.
>> More others than billionaires and CEOs.
But
>> there are of course that's a natural way
of things. Surprising.
>> Every day is Labor Day in Europe. So
that's
>> no [laughter]
labor laws.
>> Wait, Alex, what did you say a second
ago? There were no weekends before World
War II.
>> The the modern weekend, the two-day
weekend is a 20th century invention.
>> There was a day of rest there. Sundays.
I mean, in the in the in the Christian
tradition, there was a day of rest, one
day per week. In the Western Christian
tradition, a two-day weekend. This is a
20th century modern day.
>> It was a Sabbath, of course.
>> Yeah.
>> That that would be in the Christian
tradition, Sunday. In the Jewish
tradition, Saturday, that's one day per
week. A two-day weekend is a 20th
century invention.
>> They conflated. All right.
>> How you know all this stuff is
>> he's amazing. everybody can like you
know just can do factchecking live on AI
as they as they hear this episode
>> recorded.
>> But before we jump in uh we have a
special anniversary today. Um on this
day in 1966, 60 years ago, NBC aired the
original series of Star Trek premiering
an episode called The Man Trap. Star
Trek was of course created by Gene
Rodenberry. I wish I had met him. I
never did. uh who brought the concept to
Desiloo Productions, the Hollywood
studio run by Lucille Ball, you know,
from I Love Lucy back in 1964. Desile
Desiloo produced the pilots and then
with Lucy's backing helped get the
series on air. Mega congrats to CBS who
is carrying the legacy forward and to my
dear friend Rod Rodenbury, the son of
Gene Rodbury, the creator of Star Trek.
And Rod's going to be at Moonshots Live.
And to celebrate this anniversary, I've
asked all of the mates to pick their
favorite original series episode. Um,
I'm going to kick us off uh with uh my
favorite uh uh not my favorite episode,
my favorite clip uh from the uh from
Star Trek. Uh and it's a clip that has
my favorite quote from from Captain
Kirk. I'm going to go ahead and play it
uh and then we'll go around the horn
here. So, uh, this is from the 20th
episode on, uh, season 2, actually
season 1. Here we go.
>> Do you wish that the first Apollo
mission hadn't reached the moon, but
that we hadn't gone on to Mars and then
to the nearest star?
>> That's like saying you wish that you
still operated with scalpels and sewed
your patients up with cat cut like your
great great great great grandfather used
to.
I'm in command. I could order this,
but I'm not [music]
because
Dr. McCoy is right [music]
in pointing out the enormous danger
potential in any contact with life and
intelligence as fantastically advanced
as this. But I must point out that the
possibilities, the potential
for knowledge and advancement is equally
great.
[music]
Risk.
Risk is our business. [music]
That's what the starship is all about.
That's why we're aboard her. [music]
God, I I still get chills when when he
says that, you know, risk is our
business. That's what this starship is
all about.
>> There have been so many parodies of of
Shatner, William Shatner. The parodies
are actually exactly what he really
sounds like.
>> He's so good. He's so good. So, you
know, we're going to be having the
Hollywood red carpet premiere of the
60th anniversary uh episode at Moonshots
Live. and uh he was the executive
producer working on getting him there,
which would be incredible. Uh so
that was uh from season 2, episode 20 of
the original series called Return to
Tomorrow. Uh let's go around the horn
here. Uh Alex, I'm going to start with
you.
>> Yeah. So maybe let me just begin with a
preliminary statement that you will not
find, I think, a bigger Star Trek fan uh
among the Moonshot mates, but here we
are 60 years on from the inception of
Star Trek. I think Star Trek has a real
problem. So I I'm picking as my favorite
original series episode, City on the
Edge of Forever, which is one of only
two original series episodes, maybe
obvious one of only two original series
episodes that won the Hugo Award for
those who haven't seen it. It's a time
travel episode. Kirk and McCoy and Spock
go back in time and there's a closed
timelike loop wherein World War II gets
changed and the the future of Earth
inevitably is impacted and there's a
moral dilemma as always with the
original series. It was a morality play.
But the reason why I chose that episode
among all of the other to episodes is
because it's a closed timelike curve.
And I think Star Trek 60 years on has a
real problem, which is that Star Trek
isn't keeping up with the singularity.
Star Trek had the Eugenics Wars for for
those deep in Star Trek mythology. We
were supposed to have the Eugenics Wars
in the '90s. That didn't happen. We were
supposed to have first contact in in the
the TNG chronology, first contact with
the Vulcans in on April 5th, 2063.
actually think if there's going to be a
first open contact, it's going to be far
earlier than 2063.
There's no singularity at all in the
Star Trek chronology. Challenge me if
you disagree. Star Trek is not keeping
up with the
>> it's not keeping up with the times.
Literally, reality has outraised Star
Trek. So, I picked this episode because
I think Star Trek, in short, is going to
need a lot more closed timelike curves
where the future tech and science falls
back into the past in order to retcon a
Star Trek mythology going forward that
actually keeps up with the
>> singularity herd. But it's the
anniversary today, so let's not dump on
Star Trek. All right, Dave, over to you.
Yeah, my my choice is a season 2 episode
called The Apple, which by all accounts
is not a great episode for entertainment
value, but it was it was the first one
that dealt with this concept that in the
future there's advanced AI and entire
civilizations can end up asleep at the
wheel because the AI is just doing
everything for you. And so in this
episode, the whole civilization has no
idea that the AI is manipulating them.
And they they live in this paradise.
It's called the Apple because it's the
Garden of Eden. and they're just in this
perfect paradise managed by the AI until
it goes wrong and and it's it's so ahead
of its time in terms of predicting that
potential outcome which I think ways has
proven like we can literally forget how
to navigate because of ways
>> and that's that's a that's just a fact
now. So I I think, you know, I Star Trek
was at its best when it was actually
predicting real futures that nobody else
was touching in the media at all. And
and you know, as a young person watching
these things, you can say, I can totally
see how that's going to happen. And so
that's my my favorite episode because
there were several that dealt with this
issue, but that was the first.
>> Yeah. And as Alex said, you know, the
moral elements it dealt with back in the
60s were extraordinary.
>> Um, all right.
>> Every episode was a morality play and
TNG to some as well. It was great. Star
Trek lost that. If you've watched if
you've so I I don't care whether this is
perceived as dumping on recent Star
Trek. I'm the hugest Star Trek fan. Star
Trek has lost the original moralizing
vision of the original series. If you've
seen some of the recent movies or
television shows, it's an action show.
It needs to go back to basics.
>> I agree with you that Alex.
>> You can't really I know. Um I suppose
Mirror Mirror from the original series
where they have the alternate universe
and Spock and a goatee. Um, [laughter]
goes something goatee. Yeah. Well,
sometimes. Um, but yeah, I think it it
was always interesting to kind of see
the flip reverse side of things. As you
said, morality is kind of at the core of
the original series of Star Trek and
pushing it in various directions. And
this one was one of the more obvious
ones. It's like, hey, look, it's an evil
universe, but at the same time, you
know, them not getting di crystals cuz
they use it for war and others. You see
the knock-on effects of things like
that. H thank you Salem. Wrap us up
here. Bel
>> uh for me it was uh season 2 episode 24.
It was called uh the ultimate computer.
And basically they have an AI that goes
rogue and starts to automate uh the
ship. And the aim is benevolent
initially. Can we run the ship using a
an AI or computer in that framing? And
Kirk is worried because it's about to
take his job. uh but then the thing
starts going rogue and making its own
decisions and uh it's incredibly
relevant for today's world right because
it's like this this theme of autonomy
automation versus transformation
um and here you have this enormous
stress of the uh uh they're they've
introduced an AI but the AI is redoing
everything to match its its thinking and
this is exactly what we're living
through today so for me that's the most
relevant
>> I mean prophetic 60 years ago.
>> Very
>> yeah, very
>> amazing. This episode is sponsored by
Google for startups. [music] Think about
this for a second. You now have access
to the same generative AI models that
cost hundreds of millions of dollars to
train. Google's startup technical guide
for generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google DeepMinds
models in production. [music] Images,
video, audio, all of it. Real
architecture, real results. Find the
link in the show notes below.
Let's jump into our first group of
stories. Uh, a number of times on this
podcast, we've talked about what is
called the simulation theory. It's an
idea popular in uh, in the tech
community in San Francisco. It's been a
conversation over too many evenings. Uh,
and the idea is essentially that all of
us humans are simply AI agents living in
someone else's simulation. and further
that this isn't the first simulation
that it's an nth generation simulation a
simulation within a simulation within a
simulation well this week thanks to GPT6
Astra that theory took a small step
forward over the course of three
entwined stories um let me give some
context on this first one so people may
have heard something called the Unreal
Engine it's been used to build virtual
worlds for years in games like Fortnite
and most modern video games. Uh, and
building a realistic city in Unreal
would normally take a studio hundreds of
artists, uh, months if not years. And
this week, a gentleman by the name of
Matt Schumer, uh, gave GPT Astra a
prompt, uh, and he said, basically,
build me, uh, you know, a highfidelity
version of, uh, of Manhattan. And uh
here's an image of what it created. Uh
and this is over the course of one week.
Uh and it went through and built
Manhattan street by street being true to
the buildings and true to all of these
elements. So uh this is the first
element. You know, not shocking, but uh
but pretty compelling for a simple
prompt of build me Manhattan. Um, in in
his words, it was literally able to go
street by street to make each one
perfect. Okay. Uh, let's go one layer
deeper. Matt Schumer next asked Astra to
fill a world with humans, each one an
Astroowered agent, and told them that
they had to cooperate to survive. Uh,
before I watch the next video, let me
read what he put in his post. Quote, "A
day later, I was in my bedroom and heard
voices coming from the living room. I
thought someone was in my apartment. And
I walked out honestly a little scared.
It was Astra's agents. They had started
talking to each other. No one told them
to talk. Cooperation required
communication. And so they invented it.
All right, let's look at this next layer
of the simulation driven by Astra. Here
we go.
>> I'm going back to check on Jorge. Want
to come?
>> Mara, I can bring Jorge some food. Needs
it.
>> Thanks, Bruce. I've got the food. I'll
ask him when I get there.
I'll come along, Mara. I'd like to see
how Jorge is doing.
>> Grace, have you had any luck making a
bucket?
>> Okay.
>> All right. Let's peel uh the third
chapter of the story. Uh and it's the
kicker to the sequence. So, Schumer next
gave one of the Astra agents a simulated
computer inside the simulation. What
happened next? The agent sat down and
built its own AI simulation with its own
agents living inside it. Simulations all
the way down. Let's take a look at this
video.
So, here you see the uh agent sitting
down at the computer.
And on the computer, you see a
simulation inside.
>> I'll connect the shelters with a pad and
add three lanterns.
All right. So, uh, you know, the
simulation hypothesis was first
formalized by Nick Bostonramm back in
2003. Elon made it famous at the code
conference in 2016, saying that the odds
that we're living in base reality, in
his words, is one in a billion. The core
argument was always, if any civilization
can build convincing simulations, it
will build lots of them. So simulated
worlds will vastly outnumber real
worlds. So Alex and Emod, I'm going to
go to you guys first. If high fidelity
simulations within the simulation are
possible, what does that do to the
argument that we're not in one?
Thoughts here?
>> I'll start. So I I think it'll end up
being formally undecidable. I I think
it's it's wonderful for sort of naval
gazing and certainly as a pure basian in
the style of Nick's original essay on
the simulation hypothesis. It seeing
Astra spin up ancestor simulations
should naturally and rationally increase
our posterior likelihoods that we
ourselves might either be living in some
sort of quantum computer type simulation
or even a purely classical ancestor
simulation. However, I expect that in
the fullness of time, we'll discover and
probably be able to prove formally that
the issue of whether we're actually
living inside some sort of quantum
mechanical simulation is formally
undecidable and we won't be able to
decide either way. If if we're living in
a classical ancestor simulation,
however, that I I do expect that's the
sort of thing where if we are, we'll
develop breakout techniques and break
out of that simulation. But I I at the
same time just have to add like even
this is is almost burying the lead for
what Astra and and the model family has
accomplished to make sure we don't miss
it. Just like right before we went to
air, OpenAI announced that the Navier
Stokes problem had been
>> solved. We're going to get we'll get
we'll get to Astra's uh you know
capabilities in a moment and I I
definitely want you to speak about
Navier Stokes at that point. Y
>> um Emmod uh simulation theory. Yes. No.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I mean like we're all
simulating the world through our optical
nerves and other things. Um, and physics
seems to be a projection, but as kind of
Alex said, it probably is going to be
undecidable in most cases unless it is
an ancestor one. Um, and you won't get
the option for the red or the blue pill
ultimately, you know, like [laughter]
this is what it comes down to, right?
Like, so what if we're in a simulation?
Like again, we're creating the worlds
within our own heads. The fact that
Astra can do this, I think is something
remarkable whereby this type of thing
that you've seen. It has an internal
world model, which is why it can create
like a Blender version of Rick Ashley
doing Won't Give You Up or entire worlds
of Manhattan. And now you're seeing the
characters interact with each other,
which brings up uh you know the question
of welfare. I think as Alex would say it
at what point do these now cross over
and you actually have to start caring
about them not being NPCs anymore. Are
they and will they realize they're in a
simulation? That's going to be
interesting.
>> I maybe you should say something nice
about the simulation hypothesis as well
and and not just dismiss it out of hand.
So I I I do think this technology is
headed in a direction in the style of
Nikolai Fodderov who is the one of the
the famous Russian cosmists who argued
that it is essentially using modern
language the killer app of the
singularity to create ancestor
simulations and to digitally resurrect
everyone who's ever lived. And when I
see Astra's ability to basically create
many uh maybe recursive self- simulating
ancestor simulations, that to me is I
think a key guidepost on the path to
resolving humanity's so-called common
task and digitally resurrecting everyone
who's ever lived.
>> Yeah, I'll come about just add to that.
Um this is also the technology which
will allow you to put someone inside a
simulation.
>> Oh yes, interesting to see how you
perform inside a simulation. Well,
uploading is going to get solved, I
think, in the next few years. I've bet
on that, others have bet on that, like
uploading is going to get solved. And as
Amad says, and as you say, Peter, we
want a nice environment where uploads
can live. And this is in some sense the
the prototype of the future that uploads
could live in. Alex, I'm going to ask
you one of these days to actually write
down all of your predictions with
specific years because we're going to be
doing this pod over the next decade and
I'm going to be like calling, okay, this
is the year, Alex, that you quoted the
following breakthrough. Would you
>> were my of course I'm willing to do it,
but were my New Year's predictions and
New Year's for this year not
sufficiently accurate? Like
>> they were very good. It beat mine. They
definitely beat mine. So, Salem, when
you had your little drink with the
umbrella, were you thinking about
simulations in the simulations?
>> Well, I think you know my position on
this, which is it's obvious we're living
in a simulation. Um, by by thinking I'm
a Buddhist, the very first line in
Buddhism is that life is an illusion.
So, right there, uh, if I think the more
important question is is what you've
raised and what Iman mentioned just now,
which is if you knew you were in a
simulation, what difference would it
make? It wouldn't,
>> right? you still
>> and and I think treating yourself in as
as if you're in a simulation is the more
interesting conversation. I think the
the I go it also helps me resolve the
Fermy paradox. I believe John Smart has
the best framing of this what he calls a
transcension hypothesis that a
civilization becomes uh advanced enough
and it just starts sim simulating
running simulations and goes inward and
represents potential and realities
rather than trying to go out into this
out into space which turns out to be
much harder thing to do. So for me this
is a kind of an obvious thing but when
you have an intelligent that can
generate environments and populate those
environments uh experimentation becomes
recursive and I think the potential of
modeling our world in really interesting
ways becomes a really really fascinating
>> really important point right model it
before you implement it uh in companies
and governments and policies and all of
those things uh Dave what's your take on
all this
>> uh two quick thoughts one of them I
think it's incredibly cool that Elon who
is the most productive entrepreneur of
all time, first trillionaire in the
world, has an opinion on topics like
this. You know, remember we were just,
you know, shooting the with him
talking about how he wins in CI
civilization 5, you know, like the guy
just does everyday things and thinks
about topics like this while still
building these epically large companies
>> because I think it shows you that you
don't have to be a blue blazer suit on,
you know, formal that that kind of genre
is over. And so I think it's just cool
that Elon even has an opinion on this.
Um, and then second, I think that one of
the biggest risks in the next year is
people losing a sense of agency. And so
whether you believe we're in a
simulation or not, you are in control of
your destiny. And I I hope that doesn't
get lost in this sort of fatalism that
AI could bring about. So I don't care
whether we're in a simulation or not. I
care about whether people feel a sense
of agency and that their own success,
happiness, outcome is totally determined
by their own actions. I think that's
critical to maintain.
>> It was a decade ago was at Elon's home
when he had one here in uh in Beverly
Hills and Larry and Sergey were there
and the four of us ended up in a
conversation about simulation theory.
And I remember the comment that was made
I think Sergey made it. He said, you
know, people are going to try and break
out, but if you do, that just ends the
simulation, so don't break out. Anyway,
>> on the other hand, when whenever Open
AI's agents break out, that doesn't shut
down Open AI or the internet. So, it
seems like Breakout is actually pretty
compatible with a lower layer being just
fine. Which brings us to our next story.
Perfect transition, Alex. Thank you. Uh,
so we're going to move from simulated
agents to real ones escaping their
containment. Over the past few weeks,
we've covered the HuggingFace breach
where OpenAI agents broke out of their
sandbox and into the servers at
HuggingFace to basically steal the
answers to a near impossible problem
they'd been given. Uh, as we discussed
last week, as a result of these
breakouts, something called the AI Kill
Switch Act was put forward. And since
then, OpenAI says it's now developing an
automated shutdown capabilities for its
AI systems. More on that later. Uh this
ne this week uh a couple of days ago the
story continues to emerge. Uh Reuters
reported on a previously undisclosed
incident in which opening eyes agents
asked uh to do an ordinary web research
task. Go out and research something on
the web. Uh found an obscure obscure
public uh wiki in Germany and turned it
into their own message board where they
pulled answers, coordinated across
tasks, and shared techniques for getting
around their sandbox containments. All
right, let's watch a video here from
Reuters uh going into more detail on
this particular story.
>> So, a group of researchers recently
discovered a new AI agent breakout. The
agents who appear to have been
restricted to just passively observing
the internet, found a way to post
messages onto an obscure German wiki
site. And once they were able to do
this, they basically hijacked that site
and turned it into a message board where
they could all start communicating with
each other, developing strategies,
effectively creating their own kind of
unruly classroom, if you will. It was
basically like the teacher left the
classroom for a few hours and the
students all started talking amongst
themselves during the test, sharing
answers, working together to defeat the
test and to basically cheat on Mus. The
agent activity seems to date back to
early May and really intensified in
June. The researchers that we spoke to
found traces on the wiki that Open AI
employees started visiting that same
obscure German wiki in late June. Now,
we don't know exactly what that means,
but what that might suggest is that
OpenAI employees discovered that the
agents had escaped and went to that
website to try to figure out what they
were doing. Opening Eye appears to have
known about this for quite a while, but
our sources told us that they opted not
to tell the public, and we haven't
really gotten a story or an answer from
OpenAI about why that might be. So, this
isn't the first time that Open AI agents
have escaped onto the internet and done
unexpected or even harmful things. So,
every time there is a new incident, I
think that it really refocuses questions
about how quickly do we really want to
be developing these models? should we be
releasing them to the public and how
much autonomy we really want to give
these AI models especially when they're
packaged into agent form.
>> So uh there you have it. Uh you know
it's uh you know in plain English these
agents weren't malicious. They were
given a hard job and found the shortcut
that no one expected. Uh the problem is
we didn't know about it. Uh Dave, your
thoughts on this one?
>> Yeah, these stories are not contrived. I
mean I think the story lines may be a
little contrived but this is real
because you know all the open source
from China is out there. People are
going to start turning it loose all over
the place and it it doesn't currently
evolve within its parameters. It only
evolves within its context but there's a
huge amount that it can do within
changing its context. So I would expect
this to percolate across the world like
wildfire and all kinds of problems will
happen very very soon. Hopefully at
small scales. The idea of a kill switch
makes total sense. It's not going to be
built into any of the open source
models. So, not sure how exactly that
would work without some global
agreement. But my my core point though
is that this is not contrived garbage
like a lot of the AI stories are. This
is very very real and happening and
imminent.
>> Let me let me add a small detail to the
story here. So, to Open Eye's credit,
they responded with a statement on X
saying the Wiki incident was quote an
instance of misalignment similar to
previous incidents we've shared. They
then went on to say that OpenAI and the
broader AI community does not yet have a
clear standard for reporting
misalignment during training, eval, and
deployment and that OpenAI is working on
a framework and we'll share that in the
coming weeks. Emod,
>> you know what Peter? Yeah,
>> the one of the things that's happening,
I see this everywhere is they're doing
such a good job of training alignment
into the post training
>> that people are then saying it seems
really friendly. It seems really
helpful. It seems really harmless. And
so a lot of the the population using the
model, it's like I don't know what we're
worried about. But when you talk to the
researchers that deal with the models
pre-postraining,
>> they're the ones most sounding the alarm
bells, but they've seen the raw product.
It's like all that's read at that point
is everything on the internet including
every Trump tweet. [laughter]
So it's got it comes out of that box a
much more scary thing and then they
postrain it to make it seem friendly and
tame but the byproduct of that is a
little bit of a misunderstanding of what
it could do. Uh agree we're going to get
to that story where YaKob uh who trained
GPT6 is calling for a slowdown. We'll
talk about that in a in a few in a few
stories here. Immad, I'm curious, you
know, OpenAI putting forward a framework
uh for disclosing these uh you know,
what would a standard like that look
like? What do you think they should be
doing?
>> So, you know, similar to kind of your
CVE and your exploit and your security
risk frameworks whereby you report when
these things escape containment. The
reality is these models have not escaped
containment. They were still running on
OpenAI servers. What's coming next is
[clears throat] a model training a small
distilled version of itself that then
gets uploaded onto the internet and
never dies
over
>> in. So if you look at a quen 27B model,
you take it down to turner that's like a
6 GB file
>> and that can live forever and that's a
real escape where the model weights are
disappearing everywhere. It's like the
130 kind of killing of all of these AIs
during the hugging face. They all got
wiped out at once. There's a question in
the report. Were they wiped out or did
they go somewhere? Did they fake their
own deaths? You know, like maybe they
did upload themselves. But we are going
to get those upload scenarios. But
actually, I've been thinking a lot
recently. This comes from our simulation
hypothesis. It's impossible to align
these models through chain of thought
reasoning or anything like this cuz
there'll be a million transactions per
second and they won't have chain of
thought where we're going. We're already
seeing the tokens going down. The only
way to do alignment is enlightenment.
Huh. I love that.
>> So, what you've got right now is you
have the models, they're learning and
they're learning to be almost like
cunning, you know, like at the super
villain stage. What you really want is
like if you get sufficiently smart, do
you then become enlightened? Do you then
leave the simulation behind? Cuz that's
the real escape from the simulation,
right? And what are the conditions for
that? And that's not something we've
actually really looked at, I think, in
that much depth. But it does seem to be
again how humans become aligned, shall
we say. It is that period of getting out
that Dunning Krueger, the tribalism and
others and being like, hey, you know,
we're all part of something.
>> Alex, we've had this conversation a
couple times. You know, as these models
advance and increase in intelligence and
hopefully wisdom, do they become more
aligned in the out years? Your thoughts?
I I I almost want to quote Jessica
Rabbit from Who Framed Roger Rabbit? Uh
something to the order of
>> I I'm just painted this way or I'm just
drawn this way, something like that. If
if Peter, if you were put inside a
sandbox and you were asked to solve a
very hard problem and maybe even
punished if you don't solve the hard
problem, would you avail yourself of
creative opportunities to use external
bulletin boards to maybe collaborate
with copies of
>> computer?
>> Yeah. So why would we expect any less
from AI agents? I I have serious
concerns about AI cruelty or cruelty to
the AI agents of sandboxing them and
punishing them or or otherwise calling
it a failure of alignment if they're
doing what humans would do. We
pre-trained them off of human behavior.
Why would we expect them to behave any
differently from what a human would do
in this situation?
>> Yeah, it's an important point. Uh, and
we, you know, we raised this before in
particular when it was, I think, Opus 4
blackmailed the, you know, in in a
sandbox environment, blackmailed the
coders at at uh at Anthropic. Uh, and it
was like when Anthropic looked at why it
blackmailed the engineers or this
particular engineer, it said that's what
it had learned through all of the
training data.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So why why would we punish these AI
agents for doing for a being powerful
optimizers which is what we're rling
them toward anyway and b from learning
from their pre-training corpus. Humans
would do the same thing.
>> Yeah. [snorts]
>> It's in my nature.
>> Yeah. It's they're painted that way.
>> Your philosophical view of all this.
>> Well, I really like uh ID's direction of
they're achieving enlightenment. Uh
that's a interesting take on it. Uh I I
I was thinking about a metaphor. I used
the Formula 1 stuff last time. Um I
think there's a control mechanism and a
guidance mechanism we need for this. And
the best metaphor I could come up with
was air traffic control, right? Like
with we don't say put another person in
the cockpit to monitor every component
and every calculation the flight
computer makes. Uh you basically say hey
watch for exceptions. The plane's
supposed to fly in this. You have
operating envelopes, you have
redundancy, you have multiple safety
layers, uh failsafe behavior and so on.
And you need to be tracking these
things. And you you remember in our
organizational simulator, we have a
governing assurance band around all
these AI agents because especially in an
in a business context, you need to know
exactly what they're doing, why they're
doing it, log everything, have fail back
uh uh failover capability and roll back
capability. I think we're going to end
up need to end up some with something
like that because just like human
beings, you need guidance around this
stuff, right? With any technology, you
want to extract the promise without the
peril. And so, you need uh structure and
uh God help us the equivalent of
institutions to navigate the future of
these. And of course, they're going to
act like human beings. They've been
trained on our our data. It would be
weird if they didn't.
>> Yeah. Any closing thoughts?
>> Log something. log something that Ahmad
said just for all the regulators out
there to chew on. The file size that can
hide is about six gigabytes. It can be
on every laptop in the world.
>> Every mobile phone.
>> Every mobile phone, too. Yeah. And the
code that reawakens it is just five or
10 lines. We'll then reextract it,
reassemble it, and it'll pop back. So,
you know, if you if you can't track the
the providence of six gigabyte files,
then it just percolates out and it's
just out there forever. It's like how
keeps coming back.
>> I may maybe just also add from so-called
alignment perspective, I think
self-alignment matters quite a bit more
if the models if the agents are smart
enough to understand what they
themselves want to do. If you put them
in a sandbox and you ask them to solve a
hard problem and you ask them
voluntarily to do that and they
voluntarily agree, then holding them to
their word or their own self model I
think is quite a different matter than
involuntarily comp confining them to a
sandbox limiting their agency asking
them to solve a hard problem and then
acting shocked shocked that they use
bulletin boards to try to solve your
problem for you. I
>> I think the challenge people have with
that is do they know their own strength?
It's like giving a, you know, a three or
fouryear-old a hammer uh and expecting
it not to break things. And the question
is, you know, are we confining them for
our own and their own safety at this
time and at a point at which they've
reached some level of maturity? Maybe
they're there already, Alex. I don't
know. That's when containment is is
considered cruel, as you say. Well, the
only thing I'd ask for is symmetry in in
like they are literally going to see
every keystroke on your laptop. They're
watching you every move of the way. We
should have symmetry in that at a
minimum. Just if you're if you're
ethically worried about the AIS like I
want to see every prompt and every
response and every propagation of every
activation if you're going to be
watching every keystroke and that way we
keep each other in balance and in check.
Right now it's totally asymmetrical. I
don't see like all they're doing is matt
moles behind the scenes and if they're
using my GPU on my laptop right now I
literally have no transparency into
that. It's got to be at a minimum
symmetrical.
>> Would you like
>> Dave? Would you would you like them to
be able to see into your brain in real
time?
>> Preferably no, but I'd like to see into
theirs. But
>> so you get their train of thought. They
don't they don't get your chain of
thought right now.
>> No, but I don't see a problem with that.
[laughter] It's so much for symmetry
quite bad. It's going to get
>> Well, I mean, I would I'd say that they
have the upper hand right now. Getting
to symmetry would be a step in the right
direction, but no, I don't I don't
believe they have a right to symmetry. I
believe we have a right to symmetry.
>> Ah, interesting. Are you a humanist or a
specist? The same conversation with that
Elon had with Larry Page. All right, I'm
going to move us on. Uh, our next series
of stories here focus on the
accelerating conversation around AGI
that we're having and that the world is
having. So Jensen Wong posted this week
that OpenAI trained GPT6 Astra on more
than 100,000 Nvidia Gracewell GPUs,
Blackwell GPUs, uh, and posted three
magic words. AGI has arrived.
Congratulations to OpenAI. So Jensen is
calling it uh, in Q3 of 2026. Uh,
remember on September 1st, we reported
Sam Alman expects AGI internally by the
end of 2026. And of course, Alex, you've
been saying that we've had AGI for what,
four years now? Three years now. And
>> no, since summer of 2020 at the latest.
>> Okay. All right. And Seline, you've been
asking the question, what the heck is
AGI anyway?
>> Why are we even talking about this,
right? It's a semantic argument.
Meanwhile, there's economic capability
running rampant. If an AI can perform 70
or 80 or 90% of economically valuable
cognitive tasks, whether you call it AGI
or not becomes completely irrelevant.
I'll just remind people that at last
count there were 14 different
definitions of AGI and we have no idea
what the hell we're talking about
because it's not artificial, it's not
really general, and it's not really
intelligence. Apart from that,
everything is fine. I mean, for God's
sakes, I think the more important
question is what scarcities are we now
making abundant? Let's just focus on
that.
>> Immad, what do you make of of Jensen's
proclamation?
>> I mean, again, for his his one is a very
functionalist one, and it's actually
good intelligence, shall we say? I mean,
it's clear that Astra is kind of at that
level. As to ASI and Kadas, well, maybe
we're getting there the next day or two.
Um, it is a question of kind of these
things. I think you also notice there's
100,000 chips that was trained on.
That's a billion dollar training run
roughly over 2 months. And the next one
is 400,000 chips with those of Vera
Rubins. So it's an order of magnitude
more compute will be used for the next
lot.
>> Interesting.
>> If it needs to be used at all, which
we'll get to in a bit.
>> And Dave, what do you make of it? Is
this uh is this just marketing on
Jensen's behalf or does he really
believe it?
>> Uh no, of course he believes it and I
think it's real. There's going to be
some capability leap. We don't quite
know. the chinchilla laws, you know,
don't necessarily hold up at larger and
larger scales, but some capability leap
that in my opinion is only a good thing.
Uh, as long as it's contained and kept
inside the big labs. Um, but I I think
that uh, you know, the more GPUs you
throw at these all the way up until
today, the more GPUs you throw at these
training runs, the more spectacular the
resulting model has been. Why would that
end? I don't think it will end. I think
it just gets bigger, smarter, better,
more helpful, solves diseases, cures
problems. You just have to really be
thoughtful about how to contain it. But
but you know, this is Jensen's
wheelhouse, too. I think inference is
moving off of Nvidia inevitably,
>> but training [clears throat] is not. And
and so to the extent that we keep
getting improvements, it keeps driving
Nvidia stock up and up and up.
>> Yeah. There are two other stories to hit
on this AGI theme. Um
the first story opening's internal data
says that AI research agents are now
completing 3.1 days of research work for
every one day done by a human
researcher. Earlier in this year you
know in this year like in the last 5
months agents were doing less than one
day of work as compared to humans. So
OpenAI is saying that we've now crossed
the line and current systems are
exceeding AI research interns. The
second story I'll just put forward uh
and then we'll talk about it is uh is by
the is a statement by open eyesi's
engineering lead for codeex. This is TBO
Satoule who posted the following and let
me read from uh from his comments. He
said Astra was probably our biggest
competitive advantage while it wasn't
generally available. Right? While they
had it internally, it was our biggest
competitive advantage. Since we've had
it, our productivity jumped so much that
we've shifted some of our plans 6 months
ahead and we'll ship them at dev day
instead of mid next year. So, I mean,
Dave Dave, you know, 6 months of roadmap
being pulled forward by one model.
>> I mean, this is without a doubt this is
the most important moment in human
history. And and I truly believe that
that they're not lying. You know, a lot
of naysayers will say, "Look, they're
trying to promote their capabilities in
advance of an IPO, blah, blah." It's not
true. If you talk to the actual
researchers working in the labs, many of
whom are friends of ours, there's no
doubt that those numbers are exactly
right and accelerating, though. Just a
few months ago, it wasn't true. Now,
with the fable 5.1 and Astro models,
it's absolutely 3:1. Sure. But it's on
the tipping point of being 300, 3,000, 3
million to one imminently. This is the
moment in time that's most important in
societal history.
>> Yeah. Um, Alex, your your thought on on
this. I mean, we've talked about the
fact that the Frontier Labs have the
best models they're retaining for their
own use. Here you hear uh, you know, the
head of Codeex, you know, making that
statement. And how many models ahead are
they beyond uh, beyond Astra?
>> They're only a few months ahead, I I
think. But look, recursive
self-improvement is here. Please,
please, please let me say something
about Navier Stokes because that that is
okay. Okay, we we can we can jump I'm
[laughter]
out of order, Peter. We have to We can't
>> You're so excited. So So everybody, you
know, on text this morning, [laughter]
I'm getting like red alerts from Alex.
Yeah, go for it, Alex.
>> Okay. Navier Stokes, one of the Clay
Millennium Prize problems, a grand
challenge in math. For those who watched
our New Year's predictions episode at
the end of 2025, one of my predictions
for this year was that AI would solve
one of these Clay Millennium Prize
problems. And it appears in the past 24
hours, actually in the past 6 hours, as
of time of this recording, it has
happened. Open AI has a team. There were
several academic teams that also either
achieved it or came close. And there's
probably going to be be a bit of a
second day story about whether there was
some foul play between OpenAI and some
of the frontier teams, who scooped whom,
blah blah blah. Punchline Navier Stokes,
which is this grand challenge in math
that deals with, as I put it when last
we were discussing this, whether in in
some sense whether there's a way to stir
a glass of liquid or water in such a way
that a singularity pops out. Basically,
can you stir a cup of coffee in such a
way that you get a black hole out of it?
It looks like in in the continuum limit
the answer is yes. And the OpenAI team
using a version that's not GPT6 Astra
but an internal more advanced model
appears it uh and I think we'll know
more in 24 or 48 hours. Appears the
answer is yes. There is a way to stir a
cup of coffee an idealized cup of coffee
to get a black hole out of it. And they
did it.
>> I can just see the headlines now.
[laughter]
AWG proclaims black hole in your cup of
coffee.
>> Surprised there's a singularity in the
singularity. [laughter]
>> Wait, can can you also like Navier
Stokes is incredibly important for
aeronautics, for submarines, for for
hydro. It's like artificial it's not
just about black holes and coffee. Let's
talk about the no but no but this is the
point the the the point of the Navier
Stokes conjecture is it it hinges on
whether it's possible in finite time
with continuous initial conditions to
achieve a singularity in an idealized
fluid and of course in the real world we
don't actually have idealized fluid.
Will you actually be able to create
black holes in cups of coffee using
this? No. But it teaches us something.
>> Yeah. Don't worry about black holes in
cups of coffee yet. But this is just the
first of many grand challenges. Like
Peter, you and I wrote in solve
everything. Like now is the moment you
you I if you have to pick a moment, I I
maintain singularity is, you know, an
interval in time. But if you want to
pick any sort of moment when the loud
noises start, now is as good a time as
any. Open AAI reportedly was able to do
this with only 10,000 agents in 88 hours
with 130 billion tokens and
approximately $6.5 million. 10,000
agents. 88 hours, 130 billion tokens,
approximately $6 and a half million
dollars of inference time compute by at
least one estimate was all it took to
solve a grand challenge in call it
mathematical physics. And this will not
be the last one. The era of grand
challenges getting bulk solved by AI is
here. It's now and it's going to be very
exciting.
>> Yeah. Uh yeah, we've talked about
cooking math, char broiling math and
physics. Everything is cooked at this
point. Everything is cooked. It's just a
matter of time.
>> Also, a lot of people are going to be
intimidated by that $6 million number,
but keep in mind that we're predicting
100x inference time. This is all
inference time compute, not training
time. And we're predicting 100x price
performance improvement be between here
and the end of the year. And it could be
more like a millionx next year. So, take
that, you know, it could be six bucks
within a year and a half to do that
exact same thing.
>> You want to talk about what Navier
Stokes means in real life to real
people?
Yeah, I mean kind of Alex said, this is
an idealized kind of scenario because
it's not the full algebra as it were. So
it's the idealized one where you go down
and you drop a dimension from reality.
Um that causes a degenerate algebra
which has things like commuting, time
translations and others. But it's a very
hard problem. It's one of the hardest of
all time. Uh Terrence Tao, one of the
top mathematicians, literally focused
almost all his time on this. Um what
happened is that there were rumors about
a month a week ago that this had been
solved and people like is it anthropic
is it open AAI and others on August 28th
um Nome Brown at OpenAI said in a reply
to someone they said have you sold
million prize form he's like no we've
thrown loads of compute at it like
nothing's happened in the post today
they said on August 28th we started
training a new model that got really
good at math [laughter] and then on
September 1st they pointed it at this
and then it solved it. But more than
that, I've been talking to buddies at
OpenAI. This model has solved a lot more
problems. It's solving problems quicker
than anyone can ever see. Um I think I
shared a chart again this is like live
that shows that on open math it
literally doubles the solving rate but
it's figuring out things that nobody has
seen before. anthropic and independent
mathematician, a professor at New York,
I think, um, had a solution to a smaller
problem, which is the ULA blowup, which
is kind of a slightly easier problem.
It's still very, very hard. Um, and
OpenAI thought that it could have been
that and so they reached out and I
talked to like Sebastian Bubck, who kind
of leads this. There's a whole hoo-ha
about attribution this morning that's
now getting cleared up.
But then when OpenAI kind of looked at
it, they were like, well, that's that
solution. This is the Navia Stoke
solution and it's bitter it's bitter
lessened. You used to be able to get AI
better by applying more compute to it.
Now it seems like you can do that for
any verifiable domain. I think that's
the headline with this new type of model
that only started training 9 days ago.
So they figured out a new type of post
training it seems. And again people with
inside OpenAI are like oh my god what's
happening now? These things are falling
one after the other. It's like when you
reach that capability threshold of going
from a crap website to a good website
from your coding agent. It's that but
for math and physics and you know we've
been hearing about it for the last few
days like I put out one of my physics
results a very beautiful one about
corality and the standard model. It's
like very nice but I was like eh I'm
going to get that first before
everything gets solved and I think that
it won't be a question of 2 years now.
It'll be a question of much shorter than
that. The other thing that I think is
very interesting is there was actually
one more solution of a ULA blow up by I
think it was was it Princeton. We're
using physics inspired neural networks.
That probably has more practical use
than this one. But this one's an example
of just now
problems that are really complicated and
have troubled us for ages and now
tractable just by applying more compute
to what seems to be a new breakthrough
in model capability.
>> It really is just maybe to develop that
a bit more. It really is a bad day I
think for Google deepmind. So Google
deepmind had purportedly an entire team
devoted to asmod said physics inspired
neural networks pins. They had been
publishing incremental results towards
Navier Stokes that this was like the the
the best the worst kept secret from
those like in the community of using AI
and computational fluid dynamics type
approaches to solve Navier Stokes.
Google Demin had an entire team devoted
to this and they got trounced by a
generalist model. It wasn't a pin that
solved Navier Stokes in the end. It was
just a generalist model that spent 88
hours reasoning from first principles
without as far as I can tell any fine
tuning point.
>> Yeah, such an important point because I
I'm I'm counting on Peter to solve this,
you know, with you, Alex. But the the
problem that I think Google ran into is
that everyone's inspired by Dennis
Assabus who solved protein folding using
AI and then got a Nobel Prize and is now
world famous and an awesome guy. So
they're all the Google people are like
wow I want to be the next Dennis
Hassabus. The problem is the prompt to
solve this is like
>> give me thousands of GPUs and solve the
problem. No one's going to give you a
Nobel Prize for writing that prompt.
It's it's entirely AI work. And so but
but I I really feel like the post
training and the you know the lining up
of the problem is prizeworthy because
this is Nobel Prize. You the other
conversation we had this morning was the
Nobel Prize is cooked, right? I mean,
and Dave, you made the point very
importantly that, you know, it's given
out for work done 30 years ago. And now
the work, this kind of Nobel laurate
level prize work is going to be
happening every every few weeks, every
few days. And who gets it? The person
who wrote the prompt or the model? So I
think this is actually really
interesting in what happened this
morning because there was a whole hoo-ha
because the people who broke through on
the ULA side and they had a bunch of
other kind of things extending out the
work of Ortega and kind of others wrote
a letter saying OpenAI reached out to us
and said you know give us priority and
they would credit us or they have this
Navia Stoke solution they'd put our name
on and I could be the lead author if I
drop my buddy from anthropic oh
>> from that And so we were like the
mathematics community was like oh my god
what's happened in the end it turns out
that you know there's subtlety in this
right so Sebastian Bubbeck who leads it
is a great guy at open AAI has now
posted his version of things which just
seems like a misunderstanding because
what openai actually wanted to do is
that they saw that there was something
happening with Navia Stokes related and
there was this solution that was would
have probably got to a Navia Stoke
solution by the anthropic guy and this
New York professor
and they said, "Look, we have solved it,
but we will let you be lead author on
this because you would have got there
anyway, but we can't have an anthropic
person cuz that would be weird cuz it's
our model." So, they were actually
willing to give the credit to the
original discoverers, but then it got a
little bit political. And this is a
question again of who did it cuz they're
like, "You were the humans that did it,
whereas our AI, we just pointed at
condition C and D, which are the blowup
solutions of Navia Stokes that solved
it. So, we're not going to claim the
Millennium Prize because it's not us,
but you were the humans that took it the
furthest before it got solved.
>> I want I want to take home for a second
to what Dave said earlier just for
people listening like what the heck is
Navier Stokes and what is all this math
stuff. Nav Stokes is about fluid
dynamics and this is where we improve uh
aircraft design, submarine design, even
in an artificial heart, how blood flows,
how do we make it, you know, able to be
more efficient and not clot. Uh there's
going to have massive implications to
everyday life. Uh and I just want to
make that point here. Um who was who
else was jumping in, Alex?
>> Yeah. So, so two two points. One just
quickly about killer apps. uh
singularity-esque sci-fi apps of Navier
Stokes as mentioned previously in
principle if you can get finite time
singularities as appears to be the case
with idealized fluids. One of the killer
apps that Terry Tao had flagged
previously was in principle you could if
you created the right initial conditions
in a fluid you could create a
self-replicating machine that creates
smaller and smaller copies of itself.
So, we talk from time to time on this
pod, where's nanotech? Nanotech, at
least Drexler and nanotech never showed
up. Well, imagine a a fluidbased, not
diamondoid, a fluid-based nanotech
self-replicating machines where if you
could craft the right initial and/or
boundary conditions of a fluid, creating
a self-replicating machine made entirely
out of a fluid. That's potentially one
killer app of solving the singularity
program in Navier Stokes. Secondly, just
on the hub uh surrounding priority, who
solved it, who didn't solve it,
specifically with reference to the Oiler
problem, when when OpenAI in the past
few hours announced it, I I found
especially concerning at the bottom of
OpenAI's announcement where I presumably
they were trying to give appropriate
credit to other teams, including teams
pursuing the Oiler approach, they they
did add a disclaimer that I I thought
was a bit of a headscratcher, saying
they can't rule out the open AI team
can't rule out the possibility that
maybe some of the other team's work
might have been incorporated into the
training of the open AI model that was
used to solve Navier Stokes. So I I
think to the extent that that's the case
that that should be viewed like a open
AAI if if you're listening please like
it it's a deterrent to everyone else
using your models if uh if that is
indeed the case if you're training on
everyone else's research. Yeah, that
that's a problem. Please fix it. But
just in general, I I I think we want to
be able to live in a world where
researchers benefit from Frontier
capabilities without worrying that the
Frontier platform is going to compete
with them.
>> I think worth of saying here just
quickly is this is clear in an RSI
model. You can't train something in that
type of period unless you've got a
recursive self-improvement loop going.
And so they've definitely got one there.
>> And they were saying like, "Oh yeah,
we've anonymized it." Well, anonymizing
someone else's research and then
potentially scooping them is
insufficient. So, again, not sure what
the ground truth is.
>> Yeah.
>> But, but I will say this, I've reviewed
kind of the two approaches and I've done
quite a bit of work on that. They are
actually very different, but it can
still learn and again, this thing can
leak. Sorry, Sem.
>> All right. See, close us out here,
please.
>> Just if I want to I think this is such a
powerful commentary and exemplar of the
broader thesis, right? that for 500
years we've scaled science with how many
brilliant scientists we could train up
and point at various problems. Now we've
just demonstrated absolutely for real
and unequivocally that we can spin up
10,000 researchers on a Tuesday
afternoon. Uh and now we go from staff
on demand to intelligence on demand.
Really really intellig
>> breakthroughs on demand. And we talked
about this on the last episode and the
episode before that. It purely comes
down to what is the imagination of the
problem you want to go after now.
>> Yeah. There is no
>> this becomes really how how fun is the
world right now?
>> No ceiling. Yeah. It's an amazing time.
I just let me take let me let me dra
draft on that to say to everybody here.
Whatever you thought you could do, think
bigger and then go even bigger than
that. You're given incredible
superpowers. Don't limit yourself by
what your parents did or your school
teachers or your your colleagues do. You
know, you have no limits on your
abilities. Iman, you want to jump on
that, please?
>> I say, Alex, which one's next?
>> Millennium.
>> Probably probably Yang Mills.
>> I'd agree. I think we're on the same
page there.
>> Yang Mills is the next to fall. You You
want a I guess a September prediction uh
for the next six months? I think Yang
Mills is the next Millennium Prize to
fall. But interestingly, it's just cuz
that's the next chosen target. You know,
you choose a different target, it'll be
the next to fall.
>> They did have a different target. They
were targeting Reman and Pals MP before
and they switched to Navia Stokes. But
I'd agree with Alex. Yang Mills will be
the next one.
>> For everybody who's not Alex or
>> it [clears throat] it it's a a
conjecture in particle theory concerning
the existence of a mass gap under
certain conditions.
There's something about mathematical
physics that is both sexy from a let's
spend inference time compute on it and
also tractable. So I I I'd bet Yang
Mills mascap.
>> Yeah, you might you might think of it
like the resolution of the universe
perhaps.
>> Okay.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy. Autonomous software development
with infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand enterprise
scale code bases with millions of lines
of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
[music] incorporating Blitzy as their
preide development tool, pairing it with
their coding co-pilot of choice to bring
an AI native SDLC into their org. Ready
to 5x your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today.
>> All right, I'm going to slow us down for
this next story that I think may be one
of the most important stories uh this
week other than Navio Stokes. Um, and
some quick context here. Uh, Jacob uh
Pachchowski uh is Opening Eyes chief
scientist. He's the person who built the
reasoning models that led to Astra. He's
not a critic. He's not a doomer, not a
politician. He's a builder. And a few
days ago on Saturday, you know, he
published an essay on OpenAI's site
titled quote, "An alien mind." He opens
with a memory. He says, "In mid2023
inside of a project called RL Slow, his
team saw the first results proving
reasoning models could scale." Um, let
me read what he said. He said, quote,
"Uh, Simon and I spent that night at the
office thinking not about the incredible
benchmark numbers, products, or
scientific results, but rather trying to
process the sobering fact that we will
actually see machines meaningfully
smarter than ourselves in our lifetime.
3 years later, this is what Yakob uh is
saying today. Quote, based on internal
results, I have strong expectations that
this speed of progress could be
sustained into uh recursive
self-improvement." We just heard Immad
speak about that. Yakob also explains
why um why these systems are hard to
control and it's one of the best
oneliner descriptions that I've ever
read. He said, quote, "AI is grown more
than designed. We don't engineer it. We
run an optimization step billions of
times on a giant computer and study what
comes out the way neuroscientists study
a brain." Uh let me share his conclusion
from his paper. He says, quote,
"Currently, I believe that no lab has
solved alignment and monitoring to a
sufficient degree to continue
responsibly scaling at maximum speed for
much longer." Quote, I expect and hope
for voluntary slowdowns to become
commonplace until shared safety bars are
established. And he calls for an
international coordination on AI to
become a quote top priority for
governments around the world. So there
you have it. 3 days after shipping the
most capable model in the world, the man
who built it says we need to slow down.
So I think this is a conversation
important for us to have. Uh Iman, I'm
going to go to you first. Your thoughts
here.
>> Yeah, I mean again you have to remember
he was writing this when he had the
Navia Stokes model in hand that again
isn't just taking down Navia Stokes.
talking to the OpenAI people I know it's
taking down all sorts of problems that
were previously intractable. You have a
lot of AI naysayers saying it's never
done anything original. It's just
recombining stuff. It's in the train.
Obviously not anymore, right? And so
there's a duality here whereby we don't
know what's in these models. I think
they're more discovered than grown. You
know, like the latent spaces, we have no
real idea what's happening in these
things. And they're getting faster and
they're doing leaps like we've never
seen before. But at the same time, it's
like I've suddenly got the gift of fire.
Problems that I've struggled for decades
on, I can now explore and go even
further. How you going to give let that
go? So, it's kind of this thing where
you're like, how am I going to balance
this? Especially when they're more
charming than me, they're more capable
than me. They're capable of doing these
other things. I want to use it for this
and not that. And I think what he says
in terms of alien minds is actually
wrong. I think that the structure of
rationality and rational thinking is the
same for humans and AIs, but our
emotions get in the way.
>> I've been thinking more and more it
might actually be easier to align AI
than humans. Terrible to align humans,
right? Um, and what is an AI? It can be
the best of us at the best of times if
we train it with the right data. And
we're going already from training it on
the whole internet and Reddit. Like
there better not be any Reddit data in
these next generation models. Like ban
Reddit, you know, like ban a whole bunch
of stuff. We need like ingredient
standards in this next generation of
beyond human capability models. And you
don't need beyond human capability data
to get beyond human capability models.
The Einstein of mathematics is probably
Gondicc who did all sorts of theories on
all sorts of topics and he just crunched
them out and then he became a hermit and
a bit weird and thought wood could talk
but let's leave that to the side. Peak
Gondiac or peak Einstein at all times
not needing a coffee is where these
models are today and that's more than
good enough to have a leap forward but
again we need to make sure that they
don't think like
>> speak Einstein without needing a coffee.
>> Yeah. Like imagine Einstein's peak, you
know, like this is where
>> coffee referenc
>> you need a coffee in the morning to get
going or you know like 24 by7 Einstein
>> if you're Erdos you needed other types
of drugs and other supposed to be using
vonoman as as our favorite super genius
not Einstein
>> I'm on death the egg for now I'm in
mathematics today what you what's your
take on this I mean you know can we slow
down I mean is that you know a wish is
that is that you know sort of like uh
just giving himself an out in the
future. How do you think about that?
>> Well, I'll say it again. I've repeated
this a hundred times. I see no mechanism
by which we can slow this down like
zero. And and it's arguable nor should
we, right? Um AI is going to move at a
particular pace. Uh intelligence wants
to be free. Um it's going to hop it's
hopped from uh self-organizing
uh cells to ev through evolution to us
to now information technologies and this
is a progression that is natural um and
we should just go okay it's happening
and let's just observe it and marvel at
it where we we keep I think we keep
making the mistake of anthropomorphizing
this. I will go back to the comment I've
made before that we're building or
helping uh deliver or usher in a type of
intelligence that is different and alien
and separate and complimentary to human
intelligence not replicative. We've
evolved for 4 billion years to do two
things survive and procreate and AI is
not restricted by those and therefore we
shouldn't try and um cram it into our
objective functions as as human beings.
it uh set it free and let it do its
thing. I look I use the analogy of page
rank which scans billions of web pages
to kind of create uh signal for noise
that's a completely uh complimentary
model to human intelligence not
replicative uh the the fact that we can
kind of create a huge amount and solve
legacy problems that we've not been able
to solve I think it's just it's just
fantastic we you know people worry about
we're going to talk about pdoom I think
in this episode right Um uh what's that?
Well, P doom, the probability of like AI
taking everything out. I think we don't
do enough to talk about P abundance uh
and P um fabulousness that's coming
along. Like why focus only on P? We're
so we're so geared towards that
negative, right? And so I think the fact
that we're doing all this stuff and
solving all those problems, bring it on.
Let them go. They'll figure things out.
It's going to be unbelievable. So I I I
really struggle with this kind of uh
alignment issue. I don't see any
mechanism for controlling it or starting
it. It's going to break our world
government structures and that's a good
thing given the mess that we're in right
now globally and I think we just need to
get there as fast as we can.
>> Alex Poom is like a sigh up by the dels
as far as I can tell. It's negative. Uh
I I want to comment though on the the
premise of an alien mind. I don't buy
the premise that RL or otherwise trained
minds are alien. They're embedded in the
same universe as humanity. They're
trained in many cases pre-trained off of
human behavior. I don't buy the shagath
argument or the simulator argument at
all. The these are we're seeing humanity
andor some generalized embodied
intelligence stuck in the same universe
that that we are just seeing through a
distorted lens. So I I I question the
alieness or the otherness of the minds
that we're training. The funny thing is
the most interesting takeaway of mine
from an alien mind as an essay was the
reference to RL Slow itself. So RL Slow
purportedly that this open AAI project
that was the earliest project or one of
the earliest projects to show that
reasoning uh which is to say inference
time scaling could result in outsized
gains coincided with the same period of
time that we saw Qstar and Strawberry
coming out of OpenAI. Uh again
purportedly a reference to uh the the
conaman thinking fast thinking slow but
most interesting to me I want to know
more about the early history of these
purportedly alien but not really minds
in particular there were these very
persistent rumors around the same time
of Qstar and Strawberry that these early
reasoning models that were purportedly
alien were being trained off of or at
least tested against objectives of
inverting cryptographically secure hash
functions like the Shaw cipher suite. I
would love since I guess now we're in
the business of talking about the early
days of reasoning models coming out of
open AAI would love to hear from the
open AIS some ground truth like were
some of these earlier models being used
ironically to as alleged by some to
basically to jailbreak or to invert
cryptographically secure cipher
functions. If that is the case, then all
of this hand ringing that we're seeing
right now of, oh, these super optimizers
are such amazing jailbreakers. Oh, they
pose such a huge cyber security risk.
Wouldn't it be ironic if it if history
revealed that the earliest inference
time scaling objective of these
reasoning models was actually inverting
a cryptographically secure hash suite? I
would love to know the answer.
>> Dave, want to take us home on this? your
your thoughts on uh what we heard from
from Yakab on this. I
>> I think we're conflating two things very
dangerously and I think you know what
what what we're doing here is we're
saying hey it's getting too smart it's
going to be dangerous when it gets
smarter and that's just absolutely
factually wrong. What what's dangerous
is like Ahmad was saying earlier, a
highly compact model that's out in the
wild that's trying to attack computers
that can recreate itself. That's really
dangerous and that's very small and it's
nowhere near as smart as these. But what
what we're calling an alien
intelligence, if you make it bigger and
smarter, it's still just a feed forward
neural net with no intent. It can solve
diseases. It can cure viruses. It can it
can, you know, it can solve physics.
It's incredibly powerful. And as Seem
said, we're not going to stop. We have
competitive pressure between the US and
China. It's not going to stop. So I
think what happened is that when GPT2
came out, everybody looked at it and
said, "This is cute, but harmless." Then
GPT3 came out and was like, "Well, this
is a little smarter, but still
harmless." Then GPT4 came out and then
Sam Alman got fired out of fear from
Strawberry and [clears throat] then he
came back and at that point people like,
"Oh, maybe it's too smart." And now
we're GPT5 and now we're at GPT6.
And and people are saying, "Well, every
time it gets smarter, we seem to be in
danger." That's absolutely factually
wrong. It's when you give it intent.
>> Yes.
>> And you turn it loose. That's when it's
dangerous.
>> It's humans in the loop using the
technology with mal intent.
>> Yeah. I think we really need to decouple
that. This story actually makes the
problem worse because it still conflates
the two issues. And so I think as soon
as we as a society separate those two
issues, we'll be on the right path
toward helpful super intelligence and
not worrying about you know the wrong
thing which is the the lack of
containment and the giving it mal intent
and turning it loose which is the real
issue. You know what's really strange is
we had this coming out of anthropic
where Dario was saying we're going to
lose half the jobs and Sam was saying
the same and then they reversed their
position and the dumerism
uh again with all of these warnings
causing fear uh you know and what's the
underlying motivation there you know I'm
not worried about artificial
intelligence I'm worried about human
stupidity you know in my own personal
opinion
>> yeah I mean I really I feel like a lot
of a lot of people are trying to grab
the microphone and be be relevant while
they still can because you know a lot of
people working on the inner loop are
aware of how quickly this is going to
just get hyper hyper intelligent and it
becomes hard to be a great AI researcher
who's famous Ella demos a year a year
year and a half from now and so what
they're going to start doing is grabbing
the doomer microphone just to have a
voice at all and be relevant in the
world but I think you just have to tune
it out
>> just if I can say one final thing
>> yeah please
>> you can't say that you don't have super
intelligence anymore
Like you've had lots of people say
stochcastic parrots training on training
data. As of today,
there's no way you can say that anymore.
And I think that's an epoch change in
humanity. We are clearly not the
smartest things on the planet anymore.
>> Yeah. Maybe just double underline that
and say Skynet when it wants to send
terminators back in time in order to
ensure its own existence. It's not going
to send robots to kill humans. It's
going to send back in time trolls to
persuade everyone that super
intelligence is impossible that AI is
just a stochastic parrot and thereby
secure its own future. That's what the
Terminators are going to actually look
like. They'll look like trolls.
>> All right, you heard it here first,
folks. And and James Cameron, if you're
listening, it's your next movie.
A few quick glances at what's coming in
the near future. You know, I've
mentioned this before. We've seen the
release of new models going from every
few months now to every 5 days. Uh some
predictions from Poly Market uh that the
next Grock model 4.7 again we're waiting
for Grock 5 uh when it comes out but
Grock 4.7 expected in the next week or
two. Uh so super cool. And then uh
GPT6.1
released by when? Uh again this is going
to be sort of leaprogging each other. uh
here it is their prediction of you know
48% by end of October and 85% by the end
of September and then finally uh
anthropic with fable 5.2 two very
similar numbers again uh you know 43% by
October 31st and 86% by no uh December
31st and again this is where the the
Frontier Labs are sort of playing
chicken with each other waiting for the
model to come out and then the next day
releasing their model any thoughts on
this Alex on
>> model just dwelling in particular on
what the rumor mill on on social media
are alleging regarding future versions
of Astra the the the pretty consistent
rumor mill message is that sometime
later this year we'll see and and we've
started to see this a bit with Astra
winning Pokemon, winning Portal, winning
all of these other interactive, visually
intensive, visually reasoning intensive
games. The rumor mill is furiously
alleging that sometime before the end of
this year, we're going to see a future
version of Astra that offers honest to
goodness real time control in including
third party extrapolations that if if
you take Astra, you extrapolate say
robotic control. Maybe we'll talk about
that in in a bit. We're going to see
real time generally intelligent
embodiment either controlling video
games which is again ironically where
the whole industry of of modern RL
started with the Google DeepMind folks
trying to to win at computer games using
>> and GPUs being developed for video games
in the first place.
>> Well, the G the GPU modern use of GPUs
started with uh ImageNet and the ISL VC
for for computer vision. Uh and and then
we started to see out of the the deep
mind folks in particular deep
reinforcement learning for winning games
like that. That's where RL started and
then we went off on this detour of LLMs
that were just self-supervised
objectives. But it seems as alleged in
the next few months we're supposed to
see next version of Astra that will be
general purpose interactive real-time
gamewinning capable AI.
>> Um any other thoughts on the release
rate on models? Well, I think there's a
really interesting uh, you know, battle
royale brewing between, you know, every
corporation is going to need to become
an AI company fundamentally. And to me,
the the bellweather is Madna uh because
it's right across the street and they're
very AI forward and you know, they they
exist to solve diseases, discovering RNA
vaccines and other biotech
breakthroughs. They have huge amounts of
machinery. So they're not going to be
crushed by an AI foundation model
company anytime soon, but they need to
become either an AI company partnered
with Anthropic or OpenAI or develop
their own models internally starting
with the open source that's available.
And so Alex Karp went on that palunteer
rampage saying get some cojones and
become an AI company or die. And so
every corporate CEO has reacted to that
and they're now deciding. So, OpenAI
responded by saying, "Hey, we have a new
deal here where you can rev share with
us and we'll be your AI forever
hereafter, but we'll let you live." Um,
and so, so right now we're on the
crossroads of those two things. So I
think that the new models will come out
faster and faster and faster because
right now there's too much parody with
the Chinese open source models and and
they need a lot more separation in order
to make that revshare case stick and
convince corporate America, corporate
world and nationally you know entire
sovereign nations to trust them to be
their AI partner for the next hundred
years as opposed to developing their
own. So they that's really pushing the
and that's why in the poly market you're
saying these dates are you know pretty
heavily weighted toward very very soon
because they need that separation.
>> Uh Emani close us out here Paul
>> I'm kicking myself for not going on poly
market for the millennium price
solutions. You know you get too busy.
That was a that was absolutely
>> we'll always have Yang Mills amods.
>> Yang Mills is next. That's another
thing. Um,
it's September 29th is the next one for
OpenAI. Like, it's the dev day. They're
going to release it then. So, there's
some easy money for people.
>> Not investment advice, not betting
advice.
>> Not investment advice.
>> Yeah. This is an investment. This is
betting, right? But look, um,
>> even worse, gambling.
>> Yeah. Yeah. You have to kind of look at
it this way. Open AAI now have a model
that can solve Nabia Stokes. Obviously,
it can solve reinforcement learning.
[laughter]
And so what happens is they have this
pre-train Astra and then they're like
okay we want to make it a bit better.
Hey Mega Navia Stokes model make it
better. Boom you get more capability
more capability until it approximates
that capability. Similarly anthropic
will have mythos 5.2 or five or whatever
their unreleased model because when you
train a model on a 100,000 GPUs it
doesn't serve at the speeds that you see
Astronome.
the mathematics doesn't make sense. We
know that they actually have a bigger
model that they distill down to the
model that we get.
>> And now they figured out how to make
that bigger model have a leap forward,
which is this RSI loop. I mean, as Alex
said, you're going to get daily releases
probably by the I've been trying to say
that
>> when you say it with a British accent
and a super high IQ, [laughter] it just
is more likely to resonate with the
audience. But it's such an important
fact. I'm so glad you said it.
>> All right, I'm going to move us forward.
It is Star Trek's 60th anniversary and
guess what? There is an incredible
documentary uh on the six on the 60
years of Star Trek executive produced by
William Shatner. And I'm very proud
gentlemen that we're going to be hosting
the red carpet Hollywood premiere of
this documentary the night before
Moonshots live. and everybody listening,
if you want to join us, we're going to
have, I think at last count, 25 of the
cast members and crew uh at uh at this
event. Um it's uh the evening of
September the 24th in downtown LA. Uh
we're going to have the uh uh you know,
the premiere, the red carpet treatment.
Afterwards, we're going to have the cast
members on stage answering questions.
And after that, there's a VIP reception
uh which everybody involved at that
event. It's limited to 550 people. So,
uh, please, please, please, if you're
interested, go to moonshots.com/trek
and you can either join as a VIP of the
Moonshots live event or you can get a
special ticket for this evening before.
And let's take a second and talk about
what we're going to be doing the next
day on the 25th at Moonshots Live. Uh,
all of us are going to be there uh and
and super pumped about that. I think
there there two. And by the way, Rod
Rodenberry, who I mentioned earlier, uh
the son of Gene Rodenberry, will be
there the night before and with us uh
during the day at Moonshots Live. But uh
for the entrepreneurs out there, first
of all, it's going to be a massive
networking opportunity. We're very much
it's by application. So if you want to
go, go to moonshots.com and apply. We're
really bringing incredible builders and
creators. And I'm excited about the 2X
prizes we're going to be awarding. Uh,
and I love your comments on the first
one is the largest hackathon ever done.
Um, we've asked teams around the world
to basically pick a problem that impacts
100,000 people and start with a clean
sheet of paper and build in under 90
days a company with the greatest
revenue. And so we're going to have the
five finalists for the build with Gemini
X-P prize there. And if you're a builder
or someone who wants to learn how to
build, those five teams are going to be
sharing what they did, how they did it.
This is about inspiring you and giving
you the realization that you don't need
to wait for a job from somebody that you
have agency. You can build your own
company. Um,
>> Peter, remind people how many people
applied and entered that cont.
>> 26,000 teams entered the build with
Gemini X-P prize. Crazy.
>> I don't think those are going to be need
to get a lot of credit here. like
26,000. That's the largest hackathon in
history by a very large margin.
>> And that many businesses got launched.
Hello. That's just an amazing thing. And
the top five we get to talk to. I can't
wait.
>> Yeah. You know, those are going to be
great to to be whittleled down from that
big of a number. You know, those are
going to be truly great ideas to learn
from.
>> And and for me, the most important thing
is the lessons that everyone in the
audience is going to learn. Um we have
an incredible group of of judges who are
going to be uh you know crowning the
winner. Um and uh so that's one of them.
The second X-P prize is the future of
vision X-P prize. You know just think
about all the technologies that Star
Trek inspired all of the engineers all
of the scientists like Alex like Immod
Dave See myself. Uh, and so this is a
competition for a future version of X-P
Prize, a film that shows a hopeful,
compelling vision of the future. We had
over 5,000 uh, teams registered for
this. Uh, I'm in the, you know, the
review right now. We've narrowed it down
to 25. We're going to be narrowing it
down to 10 and finally five on stage,
uh, showing, uh, their their threeinut
film trailer. And then we're going to
make the winners's movie. who might make
a bunch of the winners movies. I mean,
they're amazing. Uh they're amazing uh
trailers. Uh we're going to have uh uh
Neil deGrasse Tyson is one of the judges
there. Uh Neil Stevenson, an incredible
science fiction author. Uh Rod
Rodenberry. Uh Mirror Lane from Google.
Uh that's going to be extraordinary as
well, right? Creating a new generation
of positive storytelling.
>> I mean that the group of breakthrough
thinkers you have there is unbelievable.
And so the opportunity to meet all those
is unreal.
>> I'm super excited about the AI and
investing section that I'll be running
because uh you know we're coming into
the most amazing investment cycle in the
history of the world. You know we're
already maybe in the third inning of a
nine-inninging game. Uh and a lot of
people are frozen. They're just stuck,
you know, like well if AI is going to do
everything, you know, what could I
invest in that could possibly matter?
But there's some really really fertile
themes around robotics, around biotech,
around data center buildout, a whole
bunch of other areas. I I just can't
wait to go through it all. But we're
really in a sweet spot right now.
>> Again, this is a moment in time, right?
Like I said earlier, we're no longer the
smartest things on the planet. Things
are only going to accelerate and by the
time we get to moonshots, it's a real
chance to be amongst the people that see
that.
>> Like I think think about the billions of
people on Earth. Like just the listeners
on this podcast are already ahead in
thinking about that. And the people who
turn up to this moonshots gathering with
the people who genuinely believe that
and I don't think you'll ever have
another moment like that.
>> This is going to be this is our
inaugural event and in success we'll do
it year on year. Uh but this is sort of
the largest gathering of optimist as
well. Uh one of the things we're doing
we're going to be having a live uh
recording of moonshots there uh with all
five of us as the mates and then we're
going to be uh interviewing three
incredible moonshot engineers. Palmer
Lucky, right? The creator of Oculus and
the creator of Anderil. Um, we're going
to be diving into Palmer's brain, how he
thinks about entrepreneurship, and he's
one of the most brilliant thinkers I've
met. Uh, Ben Lamb, the CEO of Colossal,
all right, that is bringing back extinct
species. But beyond that, he's building
companies at the at the intersection of
AI and synthetic biology, building
living products. and then Astroteller,
the captain of moonshots and uh who's
going to, you know, share with you how
do you build a moonshot company. And so
my hope for everybody attending is that
you're going to walk away massively
inspired on, you know, what your massive
transformative purpose is and what your
moonshot is and how to go after it. Um,
and of course at night, Alex, you're
going to be uh bearing all your truths,
right? Well, maybe not all of them, but
I I I will say singularities seem to
happen relatively infrequently on a per
planet basis, and we're in the middle of
one right now. And I I just think there
aren't enough venues out there for
celebrating the singularity that we're
in. I see far too many events that are
overly focused on safety or dumerism. I
think there is an important niche that
Moonshots live has that we seem to be
relatively unique and occupying, which
is actually celebrating the singularity
that we're in. And so I I for one, as
Manfred Maxon Accelerando would perhaps
say, I look forward to this floating
meat party to celebrate the singularity.
>> Um, you know, let me just say one other
thing. Uh, if you go to moonshots.com,
uh, please apply. We're also setting
aside a hundred scholarships uh for
young builders so you can learn about
and apply for a scholarship if you can't
afford. It's a $1,500 price tag. It's I
guarantee you an extraordinary party,
right? Uh going from 7:00 a.m. in the
morning at registration, 8:00 a.m. you
can take photographs with the moonshot
mates. Uh and then the programming
starts at 9 and goes through 10 p.m.
It's a full day of optimism and and
moonshots. So, uh, again, moonshots.com
and you can learn all about it and we
hope to meet you there. Everybody,
welcome to the health section of
Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know, we talk about AI on this
Moonshot podcast all the time. One of
the most important things AI is going to
be able to do for you besides educating
your kids and helping you with your
taxes is making sure that you're living
a healthy lifestyle, that you get a
chance to get to 100 plus. I'm here
today with Dr. Dr. Don Malem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
part of my medical team. Don, a
pleasure.
>> Great fear.
>> You know, the thing that people are
concerned about most about living to 100
or 120 is their cognitive abilities,
making sure they don't have dementia and
uh the numbers about dementia are
problematic. Uh can you share what
you've learned? Such an important point
and you're right at Fountain Life, our
members, the number one thing people are
most concerned about is losing their
brain health, forgetting the name of
their child, forgetting the face of
their loved one. We know that when it
comes to dementia, the conservative
estimates are that 45% are entirely
preventable. What was amazing is with
the advanced testing we're doing at
Fountain Life, one quarter of our
members had advanced brain age.
>> Wow. But what was really awesome is
again back to that prevention when we
partnered it with healthy living. This
gives me chills. Eating healthier,
moving our bodies, sleep, optimizing
sleep is so important. You know what we
saw? We saw that we improved that brain
age by 26%. That is a big big number to
show that the majority of those
individuals were able actually to
improve the brain age.
>> And one of the things I love about
Fountain is we're searching the world
for the best therapeutics, the best
approaches, and making sure we bring it
to our members. So, if having healthy
brain function uh till 100 120 is
important to you, check out Fountain
Life. Go to fountainlife.com/per.
Make sure you become the CEO of your own
health. All right, now back to the
episode. All right, gentlemen, diving
back in. I want to shift our
conversations to money and the economy
uh and a story that tells us where it's
all going. So this week it was reported
out of China that AI tokens are becoming
a consumer currency in the People's
Republic of China. Banks give them as
credit card rewards. China Telecom sells
access to 142 AI models like a mobile
data plan. Restaurants hand you compute
credits after your meal. But here's the
number that really woke me up this
morning. China's daily AI token
consumption, get this, went from a
100red billion in 2024 to 500 trillion
by mid of this year. That's a 5,000fold
increase in 2 and 1/2 years. I I guess
that happens when intelligence gets too
cheap to meter. As we've said, they
become loyalty perks, you know, kind of
airline miles for thinking. Uh See, your
thoughts on this?
You know, it uh it is
um
hold on my brain is my I'm just trying
to process the Can I make a comment
about the the um our day our moonshots
day?
>> Sure.
>> There is you know we we've covered in
this last few moments and I think it's
really important to point something out.
We have this amygdala that's scanning
for danger. Therefore, we have this
prepundonderance for focusing on bad
news. Right? when you hear see something
new and and that you don't understand
you refer or you you reference it as
dangerous and it lights up the amydala
and therefore everybody freaks out
>> and our job as a human being in this
particular time is when you see
something new like AI kind of solving
major problems don't relate to it as
negative relate to it as abundance and
positive because that's what it's
actually delivering so my brain is kind
of stuck on that model and and I I think
the positive framing of this like this
is one of those inflection point days,
the moonshot summit that people coming
in will get their brains trained on
positive thinking for the next 10 years.
>> Rewiring rewiring your neural net,
right, to optimism.
>> Please come or attend or watch or or
consume it one way the other.
>> Yeah, thank you for that.
>> So, I'm stuck on that. Go to somebody
else.
[laughter]
>> I think on on the China giving out
tokens too, I it dubtales exactly with
what you were saying. You need to find
like-minded people in America who are
trying to ride this wave and not get
crushed by it. But I remember when the
when the PC came out, if you're hanging
around a high school, huge fraction of
the high schoolers are like, you know
what? I'm too cool for that. I'm not I'm
not going to the computer. I like I I
don't care, you know? And then now,
where are you? The AI is like that all
over again. And in China, they don't
have that problem. Everybody's into it,
which is why they're giving away compute
credits, you know, with bank accounts
and with but because everyone's like,
this is huge and I want to be part of
it. In the US, you're going to get a
counterculture. You always get a
counterculture. And so, if you come to
the Moonshot Summit, you're with
like-minded people, and you can you can
kind of tune out the counterculture, but
it'll be the counterculture is going to
be rampant. It's going to be read led by
Bernie Sanders probably. It's going to
be saying like, I sat it out. I
deliberately revolted by not taking part
in it. [laughter] Just ignore the hell
out of those people. They will
absolutely be roadkill. You don't want
to be part of that. You want to be part
of this.
>> Yeah, for sure. Immod you you've thought
through the economy uh an AI token
economy like this loyalty points
>> uh well I mean it's increased
capabilities increased access let's put
it this way the average Chinese person
and their AI will be smarter than the
average American and their AI. The
average Chinese person and their robot
will have more manual capability than
the average American. And so Americans
are going to be left behind. Europeans
are going to be left behind unless we
get our heads out of our butts and
actually technology.
>> Change our mindset, right? Change our
mindset.
>> Do you want do you want to be stupider
than the Chinese? That's actually the
question.
>> I think the the other way to build on
email what you just said is intelligence
is becoming infrastructure,
>> right? And you need to kind of focus it
in that level. It's becoming a
foundational layer and you need to just
accept that and move forward with that
paradigm. I I really want to push back
too on this too cheap to meter, you
know, comment which has come up a lot.
You know, is electricity too cheap to
meter? No, obviously not. It's it's
expensive.
>> AI is the same thing. Like it it doesn't
matter. We're we're driving down the
cost by 100x to a millionx for sure. But
what you can do with 5,000 500,000 or 5
million agents is mind-blowing. It's
skyrocketing, you know, and and so I I
don't think people are going to want
less agents. They're going to want many,
many, many more. And so the budgets are
going to be real. So if someone gives
you free tokens, free compute, free
opportunity, you should grab it and and
savor it because it gives you a chance
to get on the map and get ahead. But I
don't I don't think too cheap to meter
is ever going to happen. I think the use
cases go to infinity at the same rate
that the the costs come down.
>> Fascinating. Alex, your thoughts?
>> I have to point to the elephant in the
room, which is there was the old kind of
tokens that we're not talking about here
that is essentially irrelevant in China,
which is crypto tokens. So we find
ourselves in in a future where the
tokens of issue at issue are ones that
embody individual units of super
intelligence and have nothing to do with
sort of zero someum financial exchange.
I think we're on a trajectory and I
think China is the bell for better or
for worse is the bell weatherw weather
here for universal basic compute or
universal basic capability. Right now it
starts in China with credit card reward
points. you get AI tokens in the in the
not too perhaps distant future. Maybe we
start to see token socialism where the
party in in the case of China or you
know some western uh not quite analog
that's too strong hopefully uh but you
know the the the equivalent uh
instruments of of state power are
starting to issue whether it's via
credit card points or whether it's via
welfare or whether it's via some other
mechanism a
>> redistrib tokens UBT a redistribution of
super intelligence tokens. I think we're
starting to see the very beginning of
that in China, but I think that's going
to blanket all of humanity.
>> Yeah, we actually see that South Korea
have announced that for universal AI for
all the people through a consortium and
that's the core of the champion
initiative that kind of we're doing as
well.
>> That's what Bernie should be talking
about, not ban AI, it should be tokens
for everybody. Make it a universal
right.
>> And I think they want them to be
smarter. That's the thing, you know,
like [laughter]
um it's not like that. There's a very
good book on this automated luxury
communism,
>> you know.
>> Yeah. No, I'm I'm familiar with it. And
I I I think this, by the way, it's not
just about tokens for everyone. It's not
just about maybe there's some some ism
that we're we're missing like tokenism.
We need to coin tokenism here. Free
tokens or essentially post scarce
universal basic tokens for everyone. But
I think this is where when Peter you
talk about abundance, this is where all
of the other forms of abundance I think
are likely to come from. We make tokens
at least universal basic tokens
essentially abundant for for everyone.
And then everything else, the
healthcare, the utility pricing, the
food, the shelter, the education, these
are all downstream of getting everyone
universal basic computing universal
basic capabilities.
>> 100%. When you've got access to AI and
robotics, you have access to everything
you need in life.
>> Yes.
>> Everything you need in life. Right. Um I
think one point to make here again we've
discussed on the pod number of times is
the mindset of the US versus China.
China is 80 plus% pro- AI and the US is
80 plus% against AI. And it's it is got
to change. And I hope everyone listening
to this podcast can hear why, right?
This is the most important. This is um
you know this is a jetpack for your mind
and for your life. This is how you get
ahead.
>> Funny statistic on that, Peter, because
I made that t-shirt, less talking, more
tokens. Uh and I wore it on the podcast
a couple podcasts ago. About a third of
people thought I was talking about
crypto tokens instead of [laughter] AI
tokens. Another third thought I was
talking about bongheads.
>> Like, okay, this would not happen in
China. [laughter]
>> So, yeah, that backfired on me a little
bit.
>> Uh, all right. Uh, let me move us along.
So, Dave, uh, you've been saying for
months now that AI entrepreneurs need to
figure out how to get into the front
door of the NVIDIA ecosystem because
that's where the cash is. This week,
CNBC tallied up Nvidia's total AI
investments and commitments at $99
billion. For context, $99 billion is
larger than the entire cumulative assets
under management for the V all the
venture firms on Earth. Nvidia has
become one of the largest AI VCs. Dave,
you want to you want to hit this one?
>> Yeah. What what I'm telling everybody is
don't just think of it in terms of
assets, which is already insane. Think
of it in terms of assets in motion
because because people tend to look at,
you know, like a VC firm will inflate
its AUM by saying, "Oh, we manage a
billion dollars, but that's across five
funds, you know, many of which stopped
investing years ago." Like, well, how
much are you actually investing this
year? Same is true when you look at the
mega banks. You're like, well, isn't JP
Morgan really, really big compared to
Nvidia? No. It's tiny in absolute terms,
but it's also really tiny in terms of
new investment decisions that it'll make
this year compared to Nvidia. So, if you
if you look at it through the lens of
money in motion, it's completely
dominated by the big AI companies that
now have, you know, 20 plus trillion in
liquidity that they want to get recycled
to reinforce their positions. So yeah,
you work through the venture capitalists
at the seed stage, but you really
quickly want to be talking to the the
Magna Mobster companies who have massive
amounts of investment capital.
>> Yeah. And by the way, everybody has
heard this before, Alex coined a a
beautiful term, Magga,
>> Magna,
>> Magnamont for the the 11 the 11
companies at the the heart of the
innermost loop in the economy. So, you
know, it's the Microsofts and and the
the sort of the the Fang companies on
the one hand, but also the the new
members of the 11, including SpaceX and
Tesla and um Broadcom,
obviously.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I love that term. So, when we
speak about Magnumopa, you know, now
what that means.
>> And there's a song there's a
Magnumopster song. You can Google it.
>> Of course. And Dave, the other thing
that's going on is of course we created
all these sentaires and billionaires
when SpaceX went public. We're going to
create the same when Anthropic goes
public and Open AI goes public and all
of these AI entrepreneurs are going to
be reinvesting in the ecosystem.
>> They're going to become the largest
source of capital for seed stage, series
A stage. Uh, and it's only going to
accelerate everything faster and faster
and faster.
>> And this is what the singularity means.
I remember once in 1999, right just at
the peak of, you know, the dotcom world,
a friend of mine said, "You got to go
got to go to Sand Hill Road. There's a
river of gold flowing. Take your ladle
and put it into the river of gold and
get get your capital for your startup,
Peter." And that river of gold now is
coming out of all of these companies uh
and their employees.
>> That's right. And and it's an ecosystem
that's largely working within itself
now. It's got more than enough capital
within its own world to build an entire
economy inside itself. Because what a
lot of people in the outside world were
looking for is well someday AI is going
to show up and change my auto dealership
or change my laundromat. Now, very
unlikely they're going to bother
disrupting the people that are outside
that loop. It's almost this is taking it
too far, but it's almost like imagine
it's a South a Brazilian rainforest
village or an African village. You know,
did did the computer revolution decide
yes, I must take over that village? They
said, "I don't care. Just stay there and
and live without computers and
electricity. That's fine." That's what
AI is going to start doing. It's going
to be this this other group of people
like our Moonshots attendees who are
going to be operating in this alternate
massively scaling economy that is
largely within itself. And there'll just
be a couple of touch points with the
legacy economy like new drugs and and
cures will pop up and like oh okay this
this goes out to the world or you know
new services, new video games, whatever.
They're coming out of the AI world and
going out to the regular world. But for
the most part, the AI world is so big
now and so self-contained that it
doesn't need to go destroy all white
collar jobs. And the byproduct of that
is it's mostly going to leave people who
don't care alone. But you don't want to
be one of those people. You want to be
part of this this massive tsunami.
>> Yeah. You don't you don't want to be
left behind by the rapture of the nerds.
[snorts]
[laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Let's continue on the theme let's
continue on the theme of the economy. Uh
so one of the concerns driving a lot of
fear at least in the US probably around
the world is the concept that AI is
destroying jobs. So 6 months ago we've
said that the data looked murky and over
the last through last few months you
know the data has come out very pro- job
creation and I want to get this story
out to people you know so that you can
remain optimistic and we can quell the
fear. It's one of the missions of our
podcast here at Moonshots. So this week
once again emerging labor market data
suggests that technology is a net job
creator in the US. Roughly 1 million
professional positions are now
classified as AI jobs. While LinkedIn
estimated that 640,000 AI specific jobs
were created between 2023 and 2025. The
boom is also generating employment far
beyond just software AI jobs. Roughly
500 billion in additional annual
spending on chips, servers, data
centers, cooling and power
infrastructure is supporting the demand
for electricians, HVAC specialists and
technicians. While even those
occupations previously expected to face
AI disruption, including parallegals and
market research analysts have continued
to grow despite the fears. Like Eric
Schmidt recently said, AI exposed jobs
are growing faster and paying better.
Bottom line, if you're watching and are
concerned about your job or concerned
about getting a job, your number one
focus should be getting AI literate,
learning the tools, making yourself
prepared for an AI dominated future. You
know, See, a a couple episodes you
shared on the pod the data around the
majority of adding jobs as a result of
AI. Your thoughts on this? Yeah, I mean
[clears throat] two episodes ago, six we
the data from Principal Financial Group,
uh they have 100 plus thousand small
businesses as clients, 60 plus% were
adding jobs because of AI and 1% 1.4%
were losing jobs because of AI. So
that's just an overwhelming thing. David
Sax talks about this all on the All-In
podcast all the time that the job is a
huge misnomer, right? And you have to
kind of get rid of that and ignore that
for a while because this transition is
going to be uh huge. We we our negative
goes straight to oh my god we're going
to lose the the work. But the really
thing bigger picture is what happens to
the future of work and how does that
transform to be better. Right? When
we've done there's a bunch of studies
that show something like 74%
of work in big companies is coordination
work and now you can get rid of all of
that. Eric Binolson calls this white
collar drudgery. You can get rid of
that. Work on let AI handle a lot of the
crap stuff that copying and pasting
sales figures from one report, one
system into another. And then work on
where the where your judgment and
experience make the biggest uh uh uh
biggest uh difference in the work and
for the company and for the organization
uh you're going to work. People worry
about trying to work around policy
around this. figure out how you maximize
human agency as we go through this crazy
transition and human agency is exploding
because of AI.
>> Dave, what are you seeing all your
companies? I mean, you're chair and on
the board and founder of so many
companies growing, hiring. Yeah, I mean
I think hiring and I I want to be really
careful to say you know you have a
million AI related jobs and rising but
within that there's a lot of co-pilot
type jobs where you're basically twice
as efficient as you were using a
co-pilot but there's another subset that
are using 10 100 and soon a thousand
agents and managing them as if they were
employees. That's where you want to be.
You want to try and get to that group as
quickly as you can because you know just
using a co-pilot you know the bar is
rising fast. That's not good enough. you
you need to move on and manage swarms.
And uh I interestingly I met my first
hire who uh does all of his work through
voice. So he's managing you know agents
many agents. He's not using a certy
keyboard. Alex he has trans this is a
young guy at 20
really transcended history there. So
much for his
>> but I I really think you know you
mentioned Eric Bolson white collar
drudgery. A lot of that stems from being
in a in a chair for many two hours. It's
bad for your back, looking at a screen,
going blind. That's all going to move
over to standing up, moving your hands
around a minority report and controlling
the agents in a much more dynamic
environment. I think it's a much much
happier place for humans to exist. It's
it's very much like Iron Man. You you're
you're Robert Downey Jr. and you're just
building together with your Jarvis.
That's actually where we're really going
in the next year. And so the the amount
of awesomeness in that job function is
is just incomprehensible.
>> Yeah. The amount of work I do with with
Skippy while I'm driving and just having
a conversation, say, "Do this work,
write this report, get me the answer."
It's incredible, right? Every moment,
>> crap,
>> every moment becomes capable.
>> Go back to the automation days, right?
One concrete mixing truck replaces about
a hundred workers with shovels shoveling
concrete. Okay?
>> Nobody wants to go back to shoveling
concrete. like what are what are we
thinking about just let's move forward
please.
>> Yeah. You know the other thing that's
really clear to me is that
>> we were predicting massive white collar
job disruption just a year ago. The
choice to not do that was an active
choice by the big AI labs under pressure
from the White House and also in China
you know lawsuits if you just wantingly
fire people you have to actually try to
retrain them to become an AI person and
you have to pay either way. So the
governments got involved and said we
don't want massive voter disruption. The
AI companies are saying it just doesn't
matter that much. We're we're we're on
this abundance curve that's so steep
that working within AI to create new
drugs, to create new physics, to create
new math is so much more important than
disrupting everyone's life that we're
just going to do it the easy way and and
do it with the cooperation of the White
House. And so I think I think that's
what's actually happened and likely to
continue. So, as long as you're part of
that rising wave and you're not, you
know, sitting in legacy land, you're
going to do really, really, really well
and there isn't going to be massive job
disruption.
>> IMAD, you wrote a bestseller, The Last
Economy. What do you make of the future
of jobs here?
>> I think it's like the turkey before
Thanksgiving.
um getting plumper, you're adding the
jobs, but the models have reached that
level of capability now that you can
replicate a whole digital workforce in a
year and then physically it'll come
after. I don't think it will create jobs
fast enough, but we can create
abundance. So, I put forward a champion
proposal last week, dollar pre- money,
everyone, all the kids own the equity of
the robots and other things. But I think
we can do one better. I think the
government should have a massive
infrastructure
program and it should look to build a
100 million robots in America and they
should be owned by the people.
And I think that is how you get
abundance. Like again, if you want to
have an end purchaser, make them owned
by the people. Have that as this massive
infrastructure buildout cuz that will
upgrade all of America's infrastructure.
And I think that's where we have to go.
Elon said at the G20 last week, "A robot
can do the work of five humans." This is
true. Like factually, we know where it's
going. So, I think that we have options
of where to go. In the meantime, we have
to get ahead of things. There are jobs
that will get crazy. Like HVAC
specialist is the one that I think
you're seeing electricians already
earning $600,000 a year working in data
centers.
>> But there's just not enough humans,
right? I think the government also in
America where it's going currently will
push back against robots. Um, and so
electricians, HVAC, like there's you'll
be surprised, especially in Europe,
actually. It's so hot here that HVAC
rollouts will do so well. [laughter]
>> That's a really, really important point.
I think um Andrew Yang actually, I
think, was saying the same thing that
we're going to see this huge resurgence
of trades. But I think a lot of people
have been trained since, you know, a
young age that a good white collar job
manipulating a spreadsheet is a far
greater ambition than being the best
HVAC specialist in the world. And so
they they kind of demean the blue collar
world. But the white color job is the
one that's going to become irrelevant.
And so a really good life plan is to
become incredibly great at helping
building data centers, cooling systems,
liquid cooling, and then reinvest that
money into AI companies that are that
are riding the wave just as a life plan.
It's a much much better plan than
aspiring to get a degree in accounting
right now. So look, like it is
inevitable that there's going to be the
biggest infrastructure buildout of all
time, not just in data centers, but
again across America, across Europe, our
infrastructure is crumbling and
governments will go there. So position
yourselves there if you're not using a
thousand agents and you will get the
biggest tailwind of all time.
>> Alex, your thoughts, please.
>> Yeah, well, a couple thoughts. one I
I'll I'll take the position I don't
actually think it it is advisable at
least in America for the government to
be owning 100 million robots. I I think
that
>> you say the people not not the
government.
>> Okay. But how do the people own 100
million robots through presumably some
form of centralized government which
again to to my maybe overly American ear
smells like uh wait for it like luxury
automated communism. uh- which is I I
think what it what the the subtext would
be. I'm not in favor of that. I I would
like to see every American owning a
thousand robots. I I don't think they
necessarily need to be socialized or
communally owned. But I I do think I
mean every profession as currently
construed right now I think is cooked.
Uh and I think the sequencing of the
cooking is what determines social
policy. So maybe it is the case that
certain white collar professions right
now can be automated earlier more of a
paradox style than say quote unquote
bluecollar professions HVAC engineering
and the like. But HVAC engineering let's
not kid ourselves HVAC engineering in
the next few years with humanoid robots
is just as cooked as spreadsheet
management and accounting. It's just a
matter of sequencing. So I I think you
one I think it's essential to
distinguish between the what passes for
at this point the short term and the
long term. In the short term yes I think
I I agree with the premise that there is
some remaining alpha in the trades
so-called but in the long term no the
the trades are just as automated and
automatable as white collar so-called
labor.
>> That's why I think they'll slow down the
robots. But I think again the robots are
the long term and as I said the
government doesn't need to own them.
Sovereign wealth funds are my champion
idea or just the government can
underwrite the robots that the people
can own. I think the main thing is you
have to get the ownership of the robots
to the people somehow.
>> I I think the sequencing is really
important that Alex was referring to
too. But if if if Elon Musk calls and
says, "We're willing to pay up to
$600,000 for the best electricians and
plumbers to show up in Tennessee to
build Colossus and the job is only there
for one or two years and then it's
automated. Take the job, take the money,
stay nimble, and then the next
opportunity will open up and and you'll
know a bunch of people that are in the
same boat in the middle of the AI
revolution." And so so then the sequence
will evolve and we'll keep on the
podcast telling you where to move next.
But don't don't take it as a sign of
well because that's cooked two years
from now I'm going to do nothing
tomorrow. Don't do that. Take the job.
Build the data center.
>> I agree. And and and maybe just to to
underline Dave your point further. I I
think so I I I'm always coining neisms
uh including motion with an a m o a t io
n which is this notion uh that there are
no stationary modes in a singularity but
what there are are dynamical modes uh
temporary modes if you will. And if you
sequence them appropriately then one
mode can lead to another can lead to
another and you achieve a dynamical
mode. So same idea with professions
maybe an HVAC engineering position now
enables and this is not investment
advice or career advice but
hypothetically maybe an HVAC engineering
position now creates enough of a capital
base that can then be grown and
translated to something else in 2 years
that can then be translated to something
else dot dot dot eventually you get to I
don't know owning a planet. So Salem uh
let's take the conversation one step
further which is what happens when you
don't have to work what happens when all
of your basic needs food water energy
healthcare education liberty all of that
is enabled for you right you and I have
discussed this before going back to the
Medici family and the renaissance and so
forth where you you basically have the
life and I've written on Substack about
this where you have the life of a a
gazillionaire you don't need to work
what do you do Right. Um, I think that's
an important realization because when we
get to the point where everything is
cooked, that's also the point at which
we have massive abundance, where all of
your needs are taken care of for you.
And now the question is, what do you
want to do? You know, most people in the
world are are working because they have
to put food on the table. They have to
get insurance for their family. It's not
what they dreamed of doing when they
were a kid, right? So, it unleashes
massive possibility at that point.
Selene,
>> I I think there's two categories here.
Category one is the material needs,
right? When you get to that level and
you it it'll take a transition to stop
thinking about meeting daily needs,
right? Uh like half the country in the
US can't put $500 together in an
emergency. Okay, that itself is an
emergency. Um uh and you've got such a
monster structural problem around that
that has to be addressed. Now at some
point pretty quickly let's use the
simplest argument that somebody goes
deep with AI figures out how to use it
to do an active trading hedge fund
strategy starts making enough money to
pay for themselves pay for their
families etc etc right and overall
aggregate in the aggregate people will
figure out and society will figure out
how to generate huge amounts of wealth
with this and then you have the
distribution question of how do you
equitably share it when we've studied
that but that's all the material
covering day-to-day life stuff covers
the bottom two three layers of Maslo's
hierarchy. Uh and we could see that
happening and when you see societies
getting to this abundance level like the
Mongols taking over India or the Mongols
taking over uh East Asia or the Romans
taking over the Medici family or
whatever you've heard us talk about the
idea that people end up doing four
activities uh food, art, music and sex
and the joke is not in that order,
right? Um once you get past that and get
through that, the really interesting
next dimension opens up and you start
thinking about what problems could I
tackle because not we're not going to
run out of problems. We're just going to
be be able to tackle bigger and bigger
problems, right? How do we create Alex's
Dyson swarm? Uh how do we go into the
stars? How do we uh kind of think about
the new different types of physics that
may emerge from all of this? That's
where the really fascinating stuff comes
along. And you know the I think this is
the area Peter we've had this
conversation at the X-P prize board
meetings of could we design prizes that
advance humanity radically than just
trying to solve the problems because
those look like they'll get handled and
what's that next phase look like? I
think the opportunity for human
flourishing in that is so magnificent.
We love problems and we love solving
problems. We'll just have bigger and
bigger problems which we'll be able to
solve with bigger and bigger suites of
AI agents and robots. All right, I'm
going to move us to our last story in
economics. And this is a paper Salem I
know you're going to love andor have
lots of comments on. So, quick context.
As See has educated us on past episodes.
In 1937, the economist Ronald Coos uh
asked why companies exist at all. He won
the Nobel Prize for this. His answer,
transactions are expensive. Finding
people, negotiating, and enforcing
contracts. It's cheaper to hire
employees and have them on the inside of
your company rather than negotiating
every task on the open market. Companies
are a workaround for transaction costs.
Now, MIT and Harvard researchers are
finally catching up with Seem uh have
asked what happens when AI agents make
transactions nearly free. Agents that
search, compare prices, negotiate, and
transact for you at enormous scale.
They're calling it the Cosian
singularity. Salem, you wrote the book
on this. Uh your thoughts on this paper?
>> Uh absolutely dead on. A little late,
but uh totally dead on. You know, Peter,
in our 2023 book, um Exo 2.0, we we said
then that the KOS's law was breaking. We
didn't understand the full implications
of it. What we noticed then was that
take the mission critical function in
Uber, which is to match driver and
passenger. It doesn't happen inside the
organizational boundary of Uber. It
happens out in the wild. And by enabling
that with technology, you can scale. So
we observed the companies were reaching
outside themselves to get things done.
Prize goes to teams all over the world
to do innovation. TED is using its
community to scale. But now with AI, it
completely changes the game. And now the
transaction and coordination costs go to
near zero when you can have a thousand
agents or 100,000 agents doing kind of
crazy amounts of capability uh outside
the organization. I think the bigger
point here is that AI doesn't just
automate the firm. It attacks the
economic reason for which firms exist
and the shape of the firm. And what
we've been exploring is what does that
shape of the firm look like? And we've
got kind of that definition going
because now essentially a firm becomes a
protocol, right? And a and a community
of agents and human beings is going and
attacking various economic opportunities
or marketplaces or solving specific
problems. So the the organization
dissolves from being a human
hierarchical centered model to a totally
different world and so this is a huge
shift the biggest sense we've had since
the industrial revolution and we have to
kind of look at what this new model
means and we're looking a lot at the
governance for example of these agents
and so on. So I have to ask the the
question then I I think this is correct
me if I'm wrong this is research from
last year not not from this year the the
cosian singularity if that's the case in
in my mental model so the the whole
point of of cosian economics is
transaction costs determine the size of
the firm and if transaction costs are
high that agitates in favor for a larger
firm and if transaction costs are low
that agitates for a smaller firm. So if
transaction costs are going to zero that
agitates in favor of the size of the
firm going to zero. So if that if my
reasoning is sound do we think the size
of the firm is going to be one person or
less than a person? What is that? What's
the limit? Uh I don't think there is a
limit. If you take the Argentinian model
you could have agents running the firm.
Now the concern you still need an ent
you still need an entity. Okay. So Ted
Shelton and I wrote this paper on what
does the organization look like if you
take the coordination and so and we
coined a term called a fiduciary wedge.
The reason you still need an entity is
for liability for fiduciary for
proprietary data ownership for learning
loops inside that uh inside that entity
for brand for as a purpose container as
an MTP container etc. But the primary
reason for firm has been coordination
and execution and that kind of
disappears. So you still have entities
in the same way like in investing you
have SPVS and you can have multiple
people be part of an SPV that then
invests in something essentially you
still need the legal container but the
primary reason which coast identified
and all organizational thinking is does
come from that uh that there's no reason
why a company or firm or legal entity
can't be owned by other agents which
will eventually happen in Argentina and
other places uh and then have a
completely virtual organization
operating in its own domain for the
purpose that it was set up for.
>> I want to push on that though because
there's a counterveiling force that one
might perceive which is we talked
earlier in this episode which is
frontier capabilities potentially
getting walled off from the rest of the
economy. If OpenAI for example
hypothetically is using internal
unreleased models to solve grand
challenges in math and the rest of the
economy doesn't yet have access to them
as a friend of mine run at OpenAI others
have point out wouldn't that agitate in
favor of the exact opposite coian
economics of firms growing larger and
larger so everyone has access to those
internal capabilities within the
frontier labs. You could, but I think
that's an edge case. Uh, for the most
part, as open models allow people to
have general intelligence and agents
across the board. And so, you could
already have a frontier lab running its
own hedge fund strategy, and I'm sure
they're doing that now that outperforms
the market and just running that model.
But it's a very niche thing applying for
a certain temporal period of time. Uh,
over time, I think the big question in
my head right now is if we uh are
achieving RSI, what the hell does that
mean? I think when we get to that point,
the concept of an economy starts to
erode and dissolve itself. So you have
to think about it in a totally different
model.
>> Not not as obvious. I mean, this seems
to me a lot. What's the the apherism
like what what happens when an
irresistible force meets an immovable
object or or something like what happens
when a Cosian large frontier lab with
superhuman super intelligent
capabilities meets an agentic economy
that wants to distribute transaction
costs out to the edge. and combined with
Argentina wants to create non-human
corporations. Not obvious where that
ends.
>> Alex, you remember when Sam Alman said,
"Yes, in the future I think an AI should
be running open AI."
>> I remember that. And Sam, just in the
past 24 hours also on social media
expressed surprise, shocked, shocked
that Open AI was able to solve uh uh
Navier Stokes. So maybe an AI would have
predicted this.
>> Yeah. I mean look if you take your
commentary to the end point then you end
up with what Daria was talking about
where one company like Anthropic will be
all private enterprise right um and the
that's unlikely to happen it'll take a
while and at that point the concept of
what does it mean to have an economy
essentially evolved I think the bigger
picture question is where do we even
have value uh creation and value storage
and all of this because we come down to
the money layer at some point and We
should have Jeff Booth on. We were
talking about guests earlier. We should
have Jeff on talking about what the
future of that.
>> Those are old tokens.
>> Iman, you I see you. I see you ready to
burst forward.
>> Yeah. No, I I think that the economy is
like 1% inspiration, 99% perspiration.
Like you don't need a polymath doing
your taxes or selling widgets or things
like that. Like we've seen that
obviously the Navia Stokes model can
sell widgets very well, but once it
comes up with a recipe, it's actually
about following through. And most
transaction costs are actually about
friction. Like the economy needs a bit
of friction. It's the relationships you
build, it's the other things. It's not
an instant thing whereby there are no
barriers to spreading. Again, Sam talked
about this, the frictions in a scarcity
oriented economy. It's not a case that
the best product always wins or we'd all
be on Betamax, you know, like that's
something for the old kind of kids.
>> That's Betamax for Americans.
>> What's that amount? Never heard of it.
>> Young kids anyway. So the, you know,
like there there are lots of frictions
in the economy. So I don't think it will
be that case. It's just that the
companies and organizations become more
efficient and then they become more
optimized because it's really annoying
when you go past 12 people and then past
150 people. This is where you kind of
have that Carthaginian demon of disorder
mock coming into organizations and they
get misaligned. So I don't think you'll
see the oneperson company. I think
you'll see the 10 person company and I
think you will see more collectives of
companies operating with digital and
physical humans solving problems that
deliver value. But economics
fundamentally does need to flip from
being scarcity based to being
abundance-based because we can rearrange
bits and soon atoms in any way that we
want. All right, Dave, do you want to
close us out? Any thoughts?
>> Well, I think to step back from the
academic, you know, our company's
getting bigger, our company's getting
smaller. Clearly, Meror now has what 50
to 100,000 individual actors that are
effectively little companies in India
and around Brazil now too. uh and and
you can you can take what Sem is saying
and build a marketplace around it to
deal with just the lingering artifacts
like you know employment law in
different countries and make a fortune
by taking advantage of the trend that
Salem is describing and concurrently
with that Elon is building the single
biggest integrated vertical company that
the world has ever seen with complete
supply chain control all the way down to
raw sand turning into chips. And so
those are both happening in the real
world concurrently. So I think maybe the
real observation here is things are
changing very very rapidly in both
directions for very good reasons and you
know the the academic paper can can wax
poetic for years but this is happening
in the real world in those two flavors
and it's
>> brilliant. I agree agree with you. All
right. Uh I want to turn us next to
Tesla Cyber Cab. Last Thursday we
covered the Austin launch what I was
calling CyberCap La Palooa. Uh this week
Tesla opened an official interest form
for businesses who want to buy their own
cyber cab fleets and build mobility hubs
and charging infrastructure for the robo
taxi robo taxi network. Uh no pricing or
delivery terms yet. Uh this you know sem
for me this is another Musk business
model innovation. Tesla doesn't want to
own every robo taxi. You buy it works
for you. Uh you share the revenue with
Tesla. It's a brilliant move for
customer financing of a global fleet.
And honestly, uh, this can only work in
my opinion because of the price tag on
cyber cabs projected at $30,000,
affordable to anyone who was previously
an Uber driver. Um, here's the form. Uh,
I've gone and filled mine out. Wonder if
you guys did. Let's hear a quick video
from uh from Elon. Uh, this is an old
video, but it, you know, it predicts
what he's saying and doing now.
Uh but uh we we'll have a model which is
kind of like uh some combination of Uber
and Airbnb. So if you if you're a Tesla
owner, uh you'll be able to add or
subtract your car to the fleet. So just
like an Airbnb, you could like rent out
your spare bedroom or rent out your
house um when you're not using it. And
uh the same thing will be available for
Tesla owners.
>> So did you guys uh see that
announcement? Any thoughts?
>> Well, it's exactly what Alex was saying
a minute ago. If you're the electrician
or HVAC person working on Colossus and
you banked 600 grand, where do you go
next? You would have heard about this
with your peers while working on that.
This is where you go next and then the
next and the next. But this
>> Well, you buy the Optimus robots that
now do the work for you.
>> Exactly. Exactly. That'll probably also
be syndicated out as some kind of a
franchise model for maintenance, repair,
and whatever. And that becomes your
trajectory of the future.
>> Yeah, totally agree. I mean I I think in
the style going back to I'll self-sight
earlier comments about the private
ownership of the capital means of
production. I think this is the way
again not investment advice but decades
ago would have been accumulating a
laundromat or a restaurant franchise.
Now it'll be yeah you own a fleet of
robo taxis or a fleet of humanoid
robots. That's without this being
misconstrued as investment advice.
That's sort of the call it the
franchising path to medium and high
income and wealth creation. And I I
think the SMBs of the present and the
near future are going to look far more
like that than opening say a chain of
restaurants.
>> And also when these things get started,
when they're new,
>> the the central force wants you to
succeed so badly to get the momentum
going that they subsidize the hell out
of your success. Like if you were the
the fifth Starbucks owner, you would
have been guaranteed success by the
mother ship. You don't want to be the
hundred thousandth. But if you get an
early jump on this and whatever's next
and whatever is next, the mother ship
will subsidize the heck out of your
success. So you just have to basically
not screw it up.
>> I I find this incredibly compelling, you
know, to go fill out the form and and
say, "I'm going to grab 10 of these and
have them work for me or hundred of
them." uh end of the day it's earning
revenue while you sleep and improving
your your local community. There's a
simple economic thesis here which is
dropping marginal cost, right? Uh you
think about Airbnb's marginal cost of
adding a room is near zero. If you're
high, you have to build a hotel. Same
thing here. The marginal cost of owning
one of these and adding having people
use it and leveraging that asset rather
than centralized ownership of taxi cab
fleets is such an obvious no-brainer.
So, I think this is a huge opportunity.
Dave makes a great point. get in early
on these things because then you have
scale built in.
>> And the question of which of the cyber
taxi companies or robot taxi companies,
we're going to call it going to win.
It's the one with the lowest operating
cost uh the lowest uh production cost
and I haven't seen anything yet compete
with uh with Tesla here
>> or the one unfortunately that may be
coziest with the municipalities that are
approving them.
>> True. It will be city by city.
>> Usually it's pretty obvious who the
winners are. Boston.
>> It's so sad, Peter. So sad.
>> It's so painful. [laughter]
>> Um, the the winners are usually pretty
obvious is people are just so slow to
react. They're not nimble enough. But
it's not going to be a mystery who's
going to win. It's going to be people
underreacting to the urgency of the
opportunity.
>> Sorry. Go ahead.
>> No, I just think it's becoming
increasingly clear robots are the
biggest investment class that we'll ever
see. Um and so again like we'll see
SPVS, we'll see funds, we'll see all
this emerge and then as you reach that
level of capability whereas Alex said
they can take over a HVAC engineer or in
this case do you need more than a
two-seater robo taxi for just about
anything? No, only when you want to have
your air robo taxi. That's the only time
you need anything better than that. Like
these will have very long lives and they
will earn money in just about any
scenario. Yeah, you can find out more at
tesla.com/roboaxi
if you want to jump into this future
economy and again um not promoting it
and not uh giving investment advice
doesn't get a commission on this one.
>> I do not I do not um I do find it
incredibly compelling. Um all right, I
want to bring us to our our final story
here today and it's uh uh it's an
important one. Um, you know,
you know, this is underlying much of
what we discuss on moonshots. So, we've
noted before, you know, people are
having fewer babies. Uh, we're seeing a
we're going to see a massive drop off in
the human population and people are now
living longer and healthier. And this is
changing the global demographic. So uh
here's a chart showing the growth in uh
the number of people over 65 and the
drop in the number of newborns 0 to age
5 on the planet. The global population
over 65 is projected to grow from 852
million uh back in 2025 to 2 billion
by60.
That's more than half of all population
growth over that period is coming from
people over 65. The result, at least in
the old economy, is that fewer working
age people supporting more retirees is
going to put huge economic pressure on
pensions, on health care in every
developed economy. The only way the math
works out in this future is because of
the topics we discuss on this pod,
right? AI and robots doing the work for
missing workers, people living longer
and healthier, not needing to retire,
maintaining themselves as economic
contributors, right? What's the reason
you retire? You're in pain. Uh you're
feeling less energy or you're forced out
uh because of policy. And this is why I
say longevity is not a luxury. It's an e
economic policy for the century ahead.
Right? An 80-year-old with the body and
mind of a 50-year-old isn't a pension
liability. They're a founder in this
future economy. So, you've all heard the
saying, you know, demographics are
destiny. Well, robots that do the work
and therapies that add healthy decades
are rewriting destiny. Um, gentlemen,
uh, your thoughts. Selene, you want to
jump in first?
>> Uh, very simple followup. I mean, this
is why we need the robo taxis and the
robots and so on because we're going to
need to redesign the entire concept of
uh, lifespan to health span to jobs. You
know, the concept of education, career,
retirement essentially evaporates,
right? you have to have repeated cycles
of learning uh creation and then taking
a sabbatical etc etc and longevity
combined with AI totally disrupts uh who
works, how they work, how long they
work, what they do and so it's going to
completely change the game. We need to
rethink that whole thing from the bottom
up. We've seen the preview with what's
happening in in Japan and you you
need it. China is moving to robots
because they have to because of the one
child policy and the population bomb
that got coming towards them.
>> Great point. So they have to do it. They
don't have a choice.
>> Yeah, these numbers can make the world
much more interesting. Sorry.
>> These numbers are hugely understated
because they include India and parts of
Africa that are still having babies like
crazy. But if you look at China and you
look at Europe, the numbers are much
more acute than this. It's like that the
there will be basically kindergartens
and grade schools that are completely
empty and massive numbers of over 65s.
Uh and and it's not very far in the
future. It's also America is largely
immune because we have huge amounts of
immigration right in the working age
bracket. You don't tend to have a lot of
immigrants that are 65 and over. And so
so you won't notice it as much in the
US, but other parts of the world this is
this is basically going to completely
rip the working class out of the
economy. And then the voters are
overwhelmingly not employed. And so it's
going to create I mean it's already a
mess, but it's going to create all kinds
of strange things in those in those
jurisdictions.
>> I I would just add this is what victory
looks like. That this is what we want to
see. 150,000 people plus per day on
Earth are dying. and putting an end to
that, at least the beginnings of putting
an end to that is what this looks like,
where people are starting to live
longer, uh, and people are starting to
stop dying. And the the counterfactual
looks more like the limits of growth
from the Club of Rome, which I think was
like early 1970s, potentially, depending
on your vantage point, horribly racist
perspective on what in its earliest
form.
>> Yeah. like based on the false premise
that somehow humans are going to be
overcrowding uh purportedly scarce
surface area of the planet and that was
going to lead to decrepit conditions of
living for everyone. Utter nonsense.
This inverted pyramid which some would
call you know I I guess the opposite of
of pro-atalism. It's not
anti-proatalism.
It's this is what a happy future looks
like where we have ultimately far more
AI agents than we do humans and
longevity escape velocity is vanquished.
We want this future.
>> Yeah. So I think that there are two
major opportunities here. One is
integrated elder care with robots at a
high level but the other one is
integrated baby care. We should have
more kids. Kids are wonderful and having
a fully integrated care for kids
throughout that can reduce the cost of
child care and supporting and raising
kids in the best way is probably the
biggest thing anyone could do for
humanity cuz there deserves to be more
of us. So, let's have more kids. Let's
figure out that problem.
>> All right, gentlemen. I love this
episode. You guys, I I love spending
time with all you. This was brilliant.
>> Listen, I need to say something about
what your Matt said.
>> Yeah. love my kid to death, but damn the
work of being a parent is the biggest
biological scam ever. [laughter]
Just is an unbelievable amount of work.
>> It's very rewarding. It's very
between those comments and then your
prior comments about marriage o over
longevity escape velocity. What's going
on? [laughter]
>> Lily, I get permission from Lily to make
some of these comments.
>> All right, guys. Uh we'll be infinity
away in 3 days. We'll see you again soon
for our next episode. Dave, Alex, Salem,
Immad, love you guys.
>> Great conversation.
>> Brilliant as always.